今天我坐下来和 Sam Altman 聊聊，他是 OpenAI 的联合创始人
Today, I'm sitting down with Sam Altman, the co-founder of OpenAI.
很久以前你在斯坦福做过一场演讲，主题是如何开始创业
A long time ago you talked or did a talk at Stanford focused on how to start a startup.
在过去大概十年里，最大的变化是什么
What is the biggest thing that has kind of shifted over the past like 10 years
从你最初做那些演讲以来
since you initially did those talks,
显然是 AI，还有如今一个小团队能做到的事
clearly AI and what is possible to do now with a small team of people has
以及你能做到的速度
and the speed with which you can do it and also.
不只是能做什么，而是在世界变化如此之大的情况下，你要怎么做才有竞争力
Not only was possible like what you have to do to be competitive given how much the
那感觉完全不一样了
world has shifted feels totally different.
一家只成立十周的创业公司现在能做到什么，让我惊叹
It is amazing to me what a 10 week old startup now can look like.
而且如果看十年前一家成立十周的创业公司
And also if you look like a ten week old startup from 10 years ago,
那基本处境很糟
you sort of are in bad shape.
你现在想到成立十周的创业公司
You think of the 10 week old startup in your mind today,
哪一家最能代表极快推进的创业公司
what is the one that is the best example of a startup that moved extremely quickly?
我甚至不知道他们叫什么，但我遇到过一家
I don't even know what they're called, but I met a,
大概只成立两周左右的创业公司
what will be a startup that is like two weeks old, something like that,
他们把办公和生产力套件之类的东西彻底重做了
that has an entirely redone sort of office, productivity suite, whatever.
全是为一个 AI 必须能使用文档的世界做的
All made for like a world where AI has got to be able to use documents,
把演示文稿、电子表格之类当作头等用户来使用
presentations, spreadsheets, whatever as a first class consumer.
我感觉这在不久之前，对一家创业公司来说
And uh, I don't know, I felt like it would have been a year's worth of work for a
得是一年的工作量
startup pretty recently.
我会假设，如果创业的门槛
I would assume that if the like barriers to starting startups
以及可用的工具越来越普及等等
and the like tools out there become more proliferated and all this stuff,
你会以为更难的创业公司变得更容易开始
you would assume that like harder startups are easier to start.
什么算难做的创业公司，正在以惊人的速度变化
What it means to be a hard startup is changing so incredibly quickly.
所以我觉得我没有一个完美的心智模型，去判断在打造一家非常成功的公司
That I don't think I have a perfect mental model for what over the many years
所需的漫长岁月里
that it takes to build a very successful company,
真正难、也真正有价值的东西会是什么
what are going to be the really hard and really valuable things?
比如，我听很多人说
Like, you know, I've heard a lot of people say, well,
现在物理世界里的一切都格外有价值
anything in the physical world is extra valuable right now
因为软件会变得免费
because software is going to become free.
但你知道，用不了多久机器人就会变得很强
But you know, like won't be that long until robots get really good and,
而很多现有的预期
and a lot of the expectations of, you know,
比如造火箭之类的事很难
it's really difficult to make rockets or whatever,
这些可能会发生相当剧烈的变化
that may change like quite dramatically.
我喜欢这样的时代，我觉得创业公司最大的优势
I love times like this. I think startups are they have the biggest edge
就出现在地面变动最剧烈的时候
when the ground is shifting the most.
当成本快速下降、周期时间快速缩短时
Um, and when costs are coming down rapidly and cycle times are coming down rapidly,
那就是创业公司
that's when startups.
真正拥有巨大内在优势的时候，而现在这种情况
Really, I think just have a massive inherent advantage and that's happening in
正在这么多地方同时发生
so many places at once right now
所以这看起来是创业的绝佳时机
that it seems like a great time to be doing startups
可大多数创业公司都是那种，我现在要去给企业垂直领域 X 做 AI agents
and yet most startups are like I'm gonna go build AI agents for enterprise vertical X now.
这在很多情况下确实行得通
That actually will work in a lot of cases.
竞争会很激烈，而且它可能并不是，事实上
It'll be very competitive and it may not be like, in fact,
我会说它大概不会是那个时代最成功、最具定义性的创业公司
I'd say it probably won't be like the most successful defining startups of that era.
它能成，但考虑到格局如此剧变
Um, but it will work but but given how much the landscape is in flux,
我很惊讶，没有更多人去做那种，我要用一整套全新的工具
I am surprised there are not more people doing the like I'm gonna go take on the
去挑战那些疯狂的事
crazy, the crazy thing with this completely new set of tools
并且愿意真正把这个事实内化
and also being willing to truly internalize the fact
也就是 scaling laws 会持续下去
that scaling laws are gonna continue.
去为那些这个月还不可能或还不划算的事做规划
And planning for the things that are not possible or economical this month,
但两年、四年后就会成为可能
but will be possible in two years, four years, whatever.
所以这看起来是个难以置信的创业好时机
So it seems like an unbelievable time to be starting startups
而且土壤非常肥沃
and there's very fertile ground.
但同时也有，我不评判人们如果选择这么做
But there's also, and I no judgment if this is what people go for,
那种巨大的诱惑，就是拿今天的 agents 去攻那些容易拿下的
there's this incredible temptation to just like go apply today's agents to the easy
胜利，我能理解
wins and I get it.
这些年你说过的一件事是，你基本上会尝试
One thing that you've said throughout the years is you basically try to,
每当你遇到一个新的人，你会试着定位
whenever you meet someone new, you try to like plot
他们在你的心智模型里，作为一个人处于什么位置
where they are on your mental model of who they are as a person.
然后下次你再见到他们时
And then the next time that you meet them,
你基本上想搞清楚他们进步了多少、进步得多快
you basically want to figure out how far or how fast have they progressed,
类似这样的事
did that sort of thing.
在也许上千个人身上这么做，会影响你的判断能力
And like doing this across maybe thousands of people impact your ability to kind of
让你能说，好，这个模型今天有这么聪明
say, okay, the model is this intelligent today,
三个月后它聪明到这个程度
it's this intelligent three months later,
突然你就能把它画成曲线，让你更容易相信这种增长
suddenly you can like plot this out and it makes it easy to believe in the growth.
我觉得这两件事背后有个共通的东西
I think there's like a general thing behind both of those,
那就是我对指数级变化产生了极大的信任
which is I just like I developed a great trust in exponentials,
无论是人、公司还是模型
in people or companies or models.
嗯，至少主观上，我不觉得看着
Um, I don't I don't think that subjectively least it doesn't feel like watching
模型进步和看着一个创始人成长是一回事
model progress is the same as like watching a founder develop
但我觉得背后对世界的那套信念体系是一样的
but I think the underlying belief system about the world is, is the same.
如果我还在给创业者当顾问
If I were still advising startup founders,
这会是我最想让他们弄懂的一件事
this is the most important thing I would try to get them to wrap their heads around.
而这显然很难，原因也是一样的
And it is evidently hard for the same reason
就像市场上还留着白捡的钱，能押注在高增长的年轻创始人身上
that there's like free money left in the market for betting on high growth young founders.
就好像市场对这一点还没完全适应过来
And it's like one of the market is still not adapted enough for that.
我觉得市场同样还没适应，模型进步的指数级增长
I think the market is also still not adapted enough for like the exponential of
会一直持续下去
model progress is going to continue
而且现在就着手做那些需要更聪明或更便宜模型的事，是完全可以的
and it is okay to start working on things now that require smarter or cheaper models.
这种不断变化的混乱，你怎么才能应对得好
This idea of constantly shifting chaos, how do you get good at it?
你怎么才能擅长在混乱环境中做事
How do you get good at operating in a chaotic environment?
我觉得就是靠练。有几件事
I think it's just practice. There are a handful of things.
我觉得不管你在理智上多明白
That I think no matter how much you intellectually understand,
都要经历很多次，才能在情绪上真正扛得住
take a lot of reps to like emotionally be able to handle
在大量混乱中做事，并相信你能想出办法
and operating in a lot of chaos and trusting that you'll figure it out
相信一切会没事，这件事不会把你搞垮
and it'll be okay and like this is not gonna be the thing that kills you.
你还不太清楚该怎么解决它
And you don't quite yet know how you're gonna solve it,
但你会想出办法的
but you're gonna figure it out.
在我看来，这种东西只能靠亲身经历去学会
This seems to me to be something that you can only learn by going through it.
而这其实是年轻创始人真正的弱点
And actually, this is a real weakness of young founders is
他们还没有那种职业阅历，去在这件事上达到情绪上的平静
that they have not had the career experience of getting to emotional peace with this.
所以早期他们会很难熬
And so they have a very hard time with it in the early days
最后他们会学会，但代价是
and then they eventually learn it, but at, you know,
巨大的痛苦、成本和本可避免的失误
great pain and cost and unforced errors.
你肯定会学会
You definitely will.
如果你最后干的是高压、有影响力的工作
If you end up in a high stress sort of impactful job,
你一定会学会应对混乱，并在其中运转得很好
you will definitely learn how to deal with chaos and function very well through it.
至少大多数人会。但我不觉得这能教
At least most people will. But I don't think it's teachable.
我觉得这只能靠自己去学
I think it's only learnable.
你很久以前说过一句挺有意思的话
You had an interesting thing that you said a long time ago,
大意是，第一次
which is basically like the first time
遇到能搞垮公司的事件时，感觉整个世界都要崩塌了
that you experience this company killing event, feels like the world's falling apart.
然后你挺过去了。到第十次时，就远没那么糟了
And then you make it through. And then by the 10th time, it's not nearly as bad.
对。你会想，前九次我都活下来了
Yeah. And you're like, well, I survived the first nine.
这次大概也没那么糟
This one's probably not that bad.
你还说过另一个想法，大概是
You also had this other idea where you said at some point,
我记得是一两年前
I think it was like a year or two ago,
你得出结论，事情总会出岔子
you came to the conclusion that shit was always gonna be going wrong.
对。所以你多少得
Yeah. And so you kind of had to, like,
内化一种能力，去享受经历痛苦、经历不顺的事
internalize the enjoyment of experiencing pain or, like, not great things happening.
呃，你是怎么完成这种转变的
Uh, how do you make that transition?
你刚说这些时，我在回想
I was reflecting earlier when you were saying this about how
我在 YC 做 office hours 时，总能看出谁是新创始人
when I would do office hours at YC, I could always tell who the new founders were.
嗯
Hmm.
因为他们面对事情严重出错时的反应，跟老创始人不一样
Because of the way that they reacted to stuff going horribly wrong versus the
因为我常常并不知道一家公司有多新
founder because I often didn't know, like how new a company was,
但我能看出这是本批次里的新创始人，还是老创始人
but I could tell if it was like a founder in the batch versus a founder.
从他们的情绪状态就能看出，他们已经干了好几年
They've been doing this for a couple of years by their like emotional state
当他们谈到某个问题时
when they talked about a problem.
我觉得大多数人以为糟糕体验的反面是好体验
Um, I think most people think about the opposite of a bad experience is a good
他们宁愿要好体验
experience and they would rather have the good experience, um,
因为那看起来更有趣、更愉快之类
because seems like more fun or more pleasant or whatever.
但如果你想想，糟糕体验的反面其实是没有体验
But if you think about like the opposite of a bad experience is no experience.
在不远的将来某一刻，你会进入没有体验的境地
At some point in the not distant future, you'll be in no experience land.
到那时，你会对糟糕的体验心怀感激
Then, you know, you can be grateful for the bad experience.
Naval Ravikant 常说一句我很喜欢的话
Naval Ravikant used to say this thing that I loved,
就是如果你的人生遥控器上有个快进键
which is if you had like a fast forward button on a remote for your life,
你的人生就结束了
your life would be over.
所以那些无聊的部分、糟糕的部分
And so like the boring parts, the bad parts,
都远远好过没有体验
it's like much better than no experience.
它们都是趣味的一部分
It's all part of the, like interestingness of
是情感的深度和广度的一部分
and the kind of like emotional depth and range.
我说不好，我觉得
And I don't know, I find it, like,
当你这么想的时候，对糟糕的日子心怀感激其实很容易
fairly easy to be grateful for the bad days when you think about, like,
难题，以及是什么让人兴奋地去攻克难题
hard problems and like what rallies people to get excited to go work on hard problems.
你们在公司内部怎么决定该攻克哪些事、什么时候做
How do you decide like internally at the company which things to go tackle and when?
什么时候该专注于核心能力
And like when you want to like focus on just your core competencies versus like
什么时候该扩大范围
expanding the scope.
我觉得清晰的使命，加上对问题的深刻理解
I think like a clear mission and then a deep understanding of the problem together
就能相当好地指出你该做什么，你不会全都做对
do a fairly good job of pointing to what you should do, you won't get it all right.
有些时候你还是会扩张过头，或者野心不够
You'll still like at some points overly expand or not be ambitious enough.
但我们非常专注于一点：这会极大地赋能人们
Um, but we are, we are like very focused on this is going to massively empower people.
过程会颠簸，但会很美好
It's going to be, you know, choppy but wonderful.
对我们极其重要的是，世界上的权力要更去中心化
And it's extremely important to us that power in the world get more decentralized
更加分散
and more spread out.
事实上，我现在最担心的风险之一就是
And in fact, like one of the biggest AI risks I am worried right now is like AI
AI 威权主义
authoritarianism and, you know,
少数人或少数公司觉得自己必须控制世界，那会非常
a small number of people or companies thinking they need to control the world that be very.
非常糟糕
Very bad.
但基于这个使命，我们觉得得想办法让 AI
Um, but given this mission, we feel like we need to figure out how to make AI
极其充裕、极其便宜、极其强大
extremely abundant, extremely cheap, extremely powerful,
把它交到每个人手里，让大家都能使用大量智能
put it in everyone's hands and like have a lot of it to get to use.
当我们看有什么挡在这条路上时
And as we look at what's in the way of that,
有一堆新的约束，比如芯片、能源、数据中心
there's a whole bunch of new constraints like chips and energy and data centers
机器人，以及构建这个平台所需的所有环节
and robots and all the pieces that need to come together to build this platform
好让我们能够
so that we can, like.
实现这个使命，你可以在这个平台之上构建很多东西
Enable this mission. Now there's a bunch of things you can build on top of that platform.
比如去做每一个垂直领域、每一家创业公司
Like you can go build every vertical, every startup.
我们没有兴趣那样去做
We have no desire to do that like that.
我认为去中心化的经济很重要，也很好
I think a decentralized economy is important and good.
我希望我们能真正擅长生产这些
And I would like us to just be really great about producing these units of
智能单元，让世界觉得，天哪，这实在是
intelligence and make the world like, man, this is just, you know,
能力惊人，而且划算得离谱
incredibly capable and incredibly great deal
我们会把它注入每一个产品和服务
and we're going to imbue it in every product and service.
所以我觉得这对我们该做什么很有指导意义
And so I think that's very instructive to us about what we have to go do.
有意思的是，通往极度充裕、高质量
My interestingly, the kind of key inputs to like extraordinarily abundant high
低成本智能的关键投入，其中很多东西比如能源
quality, low cost intelligence, a lot of those things like energy,
比如机器人，也正是充裕智能世界里你真正想要的东西
like robots are also things that you really want in a world of abundant intelligence.
如果点子很多，有各种好东西
If ideas are plentiful and there's all this great stuff,
我们仍然生活在物理世界，仍然希望事情真的发生
we still live like in a physical world and we still want stuff to happen.
所以我们得有能力在那个世界里让事情成真
So, you know, we need to be able to make stuff happen in that world.
我一直在想，能源和机器人将会
And I have wondered if, like, the fact that energy and robots are going to be
对撑起这条智能基础设施的爬坡如此重要
so important to staying on this in this intelligence infrastructure ramp.
而且紧接着你需要的东西也是能源和机器人
And also the things that you need immediately after it are energy and robots.
这到底说明了什么深刻的道理，还是只是最无聊、最显而易见的事
Um, says anything deep at all or is just like the most boring, obvious thing,
也就是要生产任何东西，包括智能
which is like to produce anything, intelligence included,
你都得操控物质
you need to manipulate matter.
但有意思的是，我们需要这些新领域
But it is kind of interesting that we need these new areas
现在要用很多算力，紧接着还要用更多
so much for what we're doing now and then so much more immediately after.
你觉得你最大的瓶颈是什么
What do you think your biggest bottleneck is?
如果说我们想让这一切毫不减速地持续扩张
Uh, if you just say like we want this to continue scaling unabated what is the
你能看到的最大瓶颈是什么
biggest bottleneck that you can see?
先是晶体管，然后是电子，就这个顺序
Transistors and then electrons in that order.
比如说像 Jensen 这样的人
So let's say, you know, you take someone like Jensen where he's, like,
他极其擅长把所有供应商都对齐到
incredibly good at aligning all his suppliers towards, you know,
他对未来的愿景上
his vision for the future.
我觉得你在这方面也非常强
I think you're also extremely good at this.
你是怎么想的，不光要让 OpenAI 跟上 OpenAI 的节奏
Um, how do you kind of think about not only keeping OpenAI on the OpenAI timelines,
还要让整个世界也跟上 OpenAI 的节奏
but also keep the rest of the world on OpenAI timelines as well.
你得和他们大量沟通，必须这么做
You talk to them a lot. You have to.
你不能只是说，我需要你
And you don't just say like, I need you to like,
在这个日期交付这台涡轮机或这块芯片，因为人家会说
deliver this turbine or this chip on this date because, you know, people will say,
好吧，随便啦
you know, okay, whatever.
他们有一堆其他优先事项
They have a bunch of other priorities.
你真的得给他们看，这是即将推出的模型
You really have to like show them here is the upcoming model.
这是它能实现的东西，这是我们的研究
Here's what it enables. Here's our research.
对我们的核心供应商
Like we're, we, we for our core suppliers,
我们真的会向他们展示很多，我们在做什么，为什么我们这么相信
we really show them a lot about what we're doing, why we believe what we believe,
它将能实现什么
what it's gonna enable.
然后你就慢慢摸索出来
Um, and you know, you figure out.
我是说，最重要的是让他们相信这个使命
I mean, the most important thing is to like get them to believe in the mission
以及为什么他们需要优先做这件事
and why they need to prioritize it.
但你也要尽可能想办法把他们的激励和你的对齐
But you also try to figure out how to align their incentives with yours as much as you can.
Charlie Munger 有句很棒的话，他说
Charlie Munger has this awesome line where he's like,
每次我以为我理解了激励的力量时
every time I've thought that I understood the power of incentives, I've, like,
我都低估了它
underestimated them.
你是怎么成功把不同合作伙伴的所有激励
How do you, like, successfully align all the incentives of the different partners
以及 OpenAI 内部的人的激励都对齐的
as well as the people inside of OpenAI?
首先，公司本身就是实现这件事的绝佳载体
Well, companies are amazing vehicles for this to start.
小时候我特别着迷于工业革命
Um, the, you know, as a kid I was like very fascinated by the industrial revolution
我把它理解成一堆技术
and I understood it as a bunch of technologies
碰巧在同一时期出现
that happened to come around the same time
又因为某种费解的原因碰巧在同一时期规模化
and for some puzzling reason happened to scale it around the same time.
我会和朋友或父母之类的人讨论
Um, and, you know, I would like talk to my friends or my parents or whatever about
到底是这项技术最重要，还是另一项技术最重要
whether it was, like, this technology was the most important invention or this one or that one.
从我现在的视角，一个花了更多时间
And my read of it from my current lens is like someone who has now spent more time
思考商业的人来看，最重要的发明是股份公司
thinking about business, is that the the important invention was the joint stock
在它被发明之前
corporation. And before that was invented.
那时都是靠信任运作的家族生意
And, you know, you had these like kind of family businesses that ran on trust
你得认识每一个人
and you had to know everyone.
当时还没有公司这个概念
And you didn't have the idea of a corporation.
真的还没有股东这个概念
You didn't have the idea of like stockholders, really?
然后突然间，这个新东西被发明出来了
And then all of a sudden this new thing was invented.
世界上的主权国家授予了这样一种新的地位
Countries like the sovereigns of the world granted this sort of a new kind of status,
真的是一种前所未有的东西
really a thing that didn't exist before,
一件非常强大的事，我们要让这些新实体出现
this very powerful thing that we're gonna let these new entities emerge
但不给它们国家的权力
and not give them the power of a state.
但给它们远超一个人的权力
But give them like much more than the power of a person.
从根本上说，这关乎激励对齐
And fundamentally, this was about, you know, incentive alignment,
责任保护，这也是一种激励对齐
liability Protection, which is another kind of incentive alignment.
还有汇聚资本的能力
Um, the ability to like amass capital
突然间你能做家族生意做不到的事
and all of a sudden you could do things beyond what a family business could do.
那种环境让人们能筹钱去开发技术
And that environment let people raise money to develop technologies,
高度投机性的，汇集资本
very speculative nature, pool capital,
想办法让不同公司在不同方向上各自专精
figure out ways to get different companies to sort of specialize in different ways
并彼此互动，严肃的金融体系和新型金融工具
and interact with each other, serious financial systems and new kinds of instruments.
这真的是件了不起的事
This was really an incredible thing.
公司这个概念在对齐激励方面发挥了巨大作用
And, and the idea of a company has done a huge amount to align incentives of very
现在一大群人 你知道
large groups of people now, you know,
数百万人可以成为一家公司的股东
millions of people can be shareholders of a company.
我们还做了很多其他事
There's a bunch of other things we do,
但我不想贬低这项了不起的发明
but I don't want to diminish what has been this incredible invention and like the,
以及资本主义在人类社会中那种夸张的超常表现 有一张图
the just ridiculous over performance of capitalism in human society like a chart
我觉得人们应该多看看 就是关于
that I think people should look at much more than they do is the like fall of
极端贫困下降的那张图
extreme poverty.
过去一百年里 婴儿死亡率 以及其他各种指标
Over the last hundred years, infant mortality and all the other things.
你想看哪个都行 任何相关的指标
Any of them that you want, any of the associated things?
如果你回头看这段历史
Um, you know, if you like kind of look back at that,
那是放到最近一百年的最放大视角
that's like the most zoomed in view the last hundred years.
但如果你回看经济增长 生活质量的提升
But if you look back at kind of economic growth, quality of life improvements, uh,
所有这些 把整个人类历史画出来
all these things and you just like drew out all of human history
再标出公司这个制度被发明的那条线
and you put the line when like the company was invented.
你会看到那之后曲线的形状有相当有趣的变化
You would see like a really quite interesting change in the shape of that curve after it.
除此之外 我觉得我们有一个使命
Beyond that, uh, I think we have a mission
它超越任何经济力量 超越其他一切能做的事
that transcends any amount of economic power, anything else could ever do.
而这可能更重要
Uh, and that's probably more important.
我觉得最有意思的一件事是
One of the things that I've thought is the most interesting is,
你有没有见过那种统计数据
have you ever seen one of those stats where it's like,
我不知道有多大比例的 CEO 是反社会人格者或精神病态者
I don't know what percentage of, like CEOs are sociopaths and psychopaths.
比例很高 我听人聊过这个
It's like very, I've heard people talk about this.
所以我在想，资本主义是不是第一个能让这些人
So I, I wonder if capitalism is the first system that allowed these people
那些极度利己的人，把激励重新对齐到
that are like super kind of self serving to like their incentives are realigned with
和社会一致，做出好产品，然后突然间你帮到了社会
societies and just create great products and then suddenly you help society
同时你自己也赢了。我确实认识很多有反社会倾向的
but you also win. Um, I definitely know a lot of sociopathic.
CEO 但我认识的最好的那些 我不会把他们归到那一类
CEOs, but I would say the best ones I know, I would not put in that category.
有很多自我极强的 CEO
There's a lot of very high ego CEOs.
那些对自己评价高得离谱的人 这种方式或许
People just like incredibly high opinions of themselves on a way that maybe,
本来会让人纯粹觉得讨厌
like would have been just like purely annoying.
但现在因为人们可以买他们的股票 也许你会
But now because people can like, you know, buy their shares, maybe you like,
对他们的讨厌和折腾多容忍一点
tolerate their annoyance and antics a little more.
所以那里确实有某种对齐的作用 我也说不好
So there's definitely some aligning thing there. I don't know.
我觉得有很多超大公司的 CEO
I think there are a lot of CEOs of very large companies
我完全不会把他们归到反社会那一类
that I would not put in the sociopath category at all.
你觉得是什么在驱动这些人
What do you think drives those people?
我是说 不同的人各不相同
I mean, it's different for different ones of them. Like?
肯定有一部分是看自己能把这场游戏玩到多好 或者能比
Definitely seeing how good they can get at the game or like how much they can get
去年的自己进步多少 我觉得这是很大一部分
better than themselves every year, I think is a huge part of it.
你知道 这在智识上相当有刺激感
You know, it's like intellectually quite stimulating.
抛开其他各种问题 你其实是在玩一场最有意思的
For all of the other problems, like you're kind of playing the most interesting
战略游戏 这可以很有趣 如果让你想想
strategic game and that can be fun if you had to think about the way
你今天做事的方式 和十年前做事的方式相比
that you operate today versus the way that you would have operated 10 years ago
假设把你放在现在完全一样的位置上 最大的
if placed in the exact same position that you are currently? What are the biggest.
这两个你之间的差别是什么
Differences between those two people.
回到上一个问题 最驱动我的是
Well, on the to the previous question, the thing that drives me the most is like,
这是我能想象到的最有意思 最重要的事
this is the most interesting, important thing I can imagine doing.
而我们现在就身处奇点之中
And we are now like in the singularity,
就是这一刻 十年前 这还像是一个遥远的
like this is the moment for the last 10 years ago, this was like a kind of far off.
顶多算个梦想 看起来非常不可能
Dream at best, um, seemed very improbable.
而现在我们真的置身于那个 我们过去
And now we're like actually in the moment that we used to, like,
在午餐桌上很不当真地谈论的时刻
talk about at the lunch table in a very not serious way.
所以驱动我的是 我这辈子都在等这一刻
Uh, and so the thing that drives me is I've been waiting for this my whole life
我觉得这会很了不起 对世界极为正面 极为美好
and I think it's gonna be incredible, hugely positive, awesome for the world.
我很兴奋能投身其中
Um, I'm excited to get to work on that.
我也觉得其他公司描绘的一些另类愿景
I also think some of the alternative visions painted by other companies are like
相当可怕
quite terrifying.
我要确保有人去对抗它 确保那不会真的发生
I'm gonna make sure that gets pushed against and is not what happens.
但和十年前最大的不同是 我们真的身处其中了
Um, but the main thing of what's different than 10 years ago is like we're actually in it.
这才是真实的
Like this is the real.
我觉得有两点都成立：它整体就是一条疯狂的指数曲线
I think it is both true that it is all one crazy exponential
而且任何单独一刻都不是那个引爆点
and any one moment is not like the tipping point.
但与此同时，我们又莫名处在又一个决定性的时期
And also that we are somehow in another one of those decisive periods
曲线可能往这边走也可能往那边走，就像我们十年前刚起步时那样
where the curve can go one way or another like it was when we started 10 years ago.
你觉得走对曲线的这一段，最大的影响会是什么
What do you think the biggest impacts are on getting this part of the curve right?
我觉得，还有一些重大的 AI 对齐问题要解决
I think like, there are still major AI alignment issues to solve
还有安全问题，也还有重大的经济问题，比如就业的未来
and safety issues and there are still major economic issues, future of jobs,
诸如此类
all that kind of stuff.
但我觉得当下真正的较量是
But I think the fight of the current moment is,
我们要走向一个 AI 威权主义的世界，还是自由的世界
are we going to head to a world of AI authoritarianism or liberty?
我们会不会因为那些非常真实的安全问题
Are we going to decide that because of the very real safety issues
和经济问题就决定
and economic issues that, you know,
让某一个模型成为“机器之神”，或者让与之绑定的某家公司来主导
we want one single model to be the machine god or the company associated to do
还是我们会说，你知道会是什么样
that or are we going to say like, you know what it's gonna be,
可能会有点乱
it may be a little messy.
但人类每一次用自由去换安全
But every time that humanity has traded off its liberty for safety, it's been.
长期看都是净亏损，所以我们要把这份力量交到普通人手里
A long term net loss, and so we are going to put this in the hands of people.
我们要赋能给他们
We're going to empower them.
我们要让社会表达自己的想法
We are going to let society express its ideas
用他们想要的方式使用这项技术
and use this technology in the way they want.
当然，要有一些护栏，但你懂的
Of course, according to some guardrails, with some guardrails, but, you know,
同时也带着巨大的力量和潜力
with a lot of power and potential.
我真的很在意我们要按这种方式来做
Uh, and I really care that we do it that way.
你和 Patrick Collison 在台上对谈的时候
When you were talking with Patrick Holson on stage,
应该是几个月前吧
must been like a couple months ago,
你说过一句很有意思的话
there was this fat saying thing that you said
大意是你每天在内部会和三四百人交流或发消息
which is basically like you will talk or text with three to 400 people a day internally.
我给人发消息比我认识的任何人都多，我不觉得这是件好事
I text more people than anybody else I know. I don't think this is, like, a good thing.
我其实觉得这算是个坏习惯。为什么
I think this is actually, uh, like a bad habit. Why?
因为它占了我大部分时间，而且让我变得
Um, because it takes up like most of my time and I get like into,
我现在注意力很难集中
I have a very short attention span now.
有意思
Interesting.
这让你能做到什么，否则做不到的事
What does that enable you to do that? Like otherwise,
我掌握了海量的上下文
I have a huge amount of context.
我就像一个不算太聪明的 AI 模型，但拥有极大量的
I mean, I'm like a AI model that's not that smart, but just has like a huge amount,
一种关于此刻正在发生的一切的短期上下文，然后就忘了
like a short term context on like whatever's happening right now and then forget.
这能让你做出别人做不出的决策吗
Does that enable you to make decisions that other people wouldn't have?
比如哪些公司决策，是更好还是不好
Like what company decisions better or not?
我不知道。反正它让我能做出跟别人不一样的决策
I don't know. I mean, it lets me make different decisions than other people would.
在过去大概 12 个月里，你做过哪些不一样的决策
What different decisions would you have you made in the last like 12 months
如果没有这么多上下文，你就不会那样做
that you wouldn't have made if you didn't have so much context?
我不确定有没有一个能公开分享的具体例子
I don't know if I have like a specific one I can share publicly,
但有很多情况是，因为我
but there's like a lot of things where, you know, because I,
我知道某个即将到来的研究突破，会影响到
I know about some random research breakthrough impending that is gonna like affect
某个客户或某个供应商之类的
some customer or some supplier, whatever,
我就能在那一刻做出略微不同的决策。而如果我当时不知道
I can make a slightly different decision in the moment. And if I hadn't known.
如果那天早上不知道，我就会做出另一个决策，而且会更糟
It that morning, I would have made a different decision. It would have been worse.
我觉得你最擅长的一件事，就是那种长期
One of the things that I think you are the best at is kind of like long term
思考，但同时事情又变化得这么快
thinking and yet it also seems like things are moving so quickly
世界变得这么快，做二十年的规划
and the world is changing so fast that planning 20 years out
然后再往回倒推
and then like looking backwards.
我都不确定这还说不说得通
I don't even know if that makes sense.
你怎么看这个？你的时间视野是不是在缩短
How do you think about this? How is like, is your time horizon shortening?
我其实不会去做倒推式的规划
I actually don't try to plan backwards.
我会尽量对未来抱有少数几个坚定的信念
I try to have like a, a small number of strongly held convictions about the future
那种大方向大致会朝哪走的信念
that are like direction tends to head towards,
然后我会从当前的状态往前规划，想我们现在能
but then I try to like plan forwards from the current state about like what can we
做什么，今年能做什么？有时候你确实
do now, what can we do this year? And sometimes you do.
得在五年或十年的时间尺度上规划一些事
Have to, like, plan a few things on a, you know, five or 10 year horizon.
但我尽量往前规划，由对未来的少数几个信念来指引
But I try to plan forward guided to a small number of beliefs about the future.
我觉得很多人对未来抱着太多信念
I think there are a lot of people who have way too many beliefs about the future
还有一套僵化的世界观，硬要把一切往里套
and a kind of rigid worldview that they try to fit.
结果就是他们最后一直在追
And then but what happens is they end up like chasing, you know,
你会看到航天公司变成 AI 公司之类的
you see like space companies turn into AI companies or whatever.
而只对未来
Um, and like having just a small number of things
保有少数几个深层信念，其余都非常灵活
that you deeply believe about the future and being very flexible on the rest, um,
并且始终忠于核心，这很有帮助
and staying very true to the core is, is helpful.
我最了解的人之一，他公司的头号
One of the people that I know the best, his top, you know,
核心价值就是关键路径，只聚焦在关键路径上
company core value is just critical path and just focusing on the critical path
始终盯住最大障碍背后的关键驱动因素
and like staying focused on the key drivers of whatever the biggest roadblock is,
把它搞定，再去下一个，如此循环
just unfuck that and then go to the next one and do that again. How do.
你在自己人生里
You think about critical path in your own life
做这些决定时，是怎么看关键路径的
when you're kind of like trying to make these decisions.
这么久以来，我一直专注于一个唯一目标：充裕智能
I mean, for so long now, I have felt focused on the singular goal of abundant intelligence.
我相信这会带来难以想象的人类繁荣
And a belief that, like, incredible human prosperity will come from that as long
只要我们不出现某种诡异的权力集中
as we don't have a weird power concentration
以及某种新型威权主义
and kind of a new kind of authoritarianism.
任何时候我都很清楚，通往那里的关键路径是什么
It has been fairly clear to me at any given time what's on the critical path to get there.
我从来没有被诱惑去想
And I have not been tempted by, you know,
我是不是该重新考虑目标，或者去想那些别的事
should I reconsider the goal or should I think about these other things?
最近我确实开始多想一点：好吧
I have been thinking about that a little bit more recently of like, okay,
如果我们真的接近超级智能了，那下一步是什么
if we really are close to super intelligence, it's what's next?
但这就是我主观上的感受
But but it's this that's kind of how I, I subjectively feel.
我们已经很近了
We are close.
这是十多年来我第一次去想
This is the first time in like more than a decade I've thought about what is the
下一件事是什么，会不会就是那个农场
next thing and is it the ranch?
我是说，最终也许会有那个农场，中间还有几件事
Uh, I mean, eventually there might be some the ranch, a few more things on the way.
但没错，那是最终的计划
But that is, yes, that is the eventual plan.
如果让你猜，Sam 在归隐农场之前
If you had to like try to guess what else does Sam want to accomplish
还想完成什么
before he ranches?
你看，AI 超级智能一定会被造出来
Um, look, AI super intelligence is gonna get built like that, you know,
还没完成，但我们已经在通往那里的滑翔路径上了
not done but like gonna we are we are on the glide path to they get there is very um,
充裕、去中心化、广泛可及，并确保
abundance and decentralize and like wide access to it and making sure
它最终带来广泛共享的繁荣
that it ends up with like broadly shared prosperity.
我真的很想实现这个
I'd really like to accomplish that.
所以也许这就是我一直在想的下一件事
So maybe that that's the thing that I've been like thinking about as the next thing,
就是我们在技术上要怎么完成使命
like how does technologically we're going to accomplish our mission.
我觉得我们很多的世界观、很多关于安全的信念
I think a lot of our worldview and a lot of our beliefs about safety
以及它会带来的影响，这些我们也都做到了
and the impact is going to have, have also, we've gotten those things done, too.
但你知道，非常广泛的共享繁荣
Um, but, you know, very broadly, shared prosperity and, uh,
真正专注于赋能这个世界
a real focus on enabling the world here.
这看起来非常重要
Um, that seems very important.
我一次又一次听你说起
I've heard you say again and again, uh,
在临界情况下也要上飞机这个想法
this idea of get on planes in marginal situations.
我这么做过无数次
I've done this a huge number of times.
到目前为止效果都不错。挺好，我觉得
Uh, so far it's working pretty well. Good, I think, I think it's,
我觉得这是非常靠谱的建议
I think it's very solid advice.
你上一次在临界情况下上飞机是什么时候
When was the last time that you got on a plane in a marginal situation?
我不能说是为了什么，但就在最近，结果很好
Well, I can't say what for, but very recently and it worked out.
恭喜。谢谢
Congratulations. Thank you.
我真的很不想去。那是很不方便的两晚行程
And I really didn't want to. It was like a very inconvenient two overnights.
本来不想去。刚有了孩子，一团乱。但结果其实还不错
Didn't want to do it. New baby, whole mess. But I did okay, actually.
带我进入你决定做那次全球巡回的思考过程
Take me into your, like, mental process for deciding to do this world tour
我是说，很难倒回三年前
that is just, I mean it again, it's like hard to rewind three years
因为现在感觉 AI 好像一直都在
because now like it feels like AI has been here forever.
但三年前
But three years ago.
我们刚发布 GPT-4，整个世界都炸了
We had just launched GPT 4. The world was melting down.
所有人都慌了
Everybody was freaking out.
所有人都在喊，天哪
Everybody was just like, oh, man.
没人知道该怎么想
And no one knew what to think.
我能感觉到那种…
And I could just feel these, like,
山雨欲来的感觉 大家都在动怒 那些世界领导人也是
storm clouds brewing and like people just getting angry or it was like world leaders
他们在想 我们是不是得接管 然后把它关掉
were like, do we need to like take control and shut things down?
这东西是不是要觉醒了 那真是段诡异的时期
Like is this thing waking up in about it was it was weird time and
因为一切发生得太快了
because it had all happened so fast,
人们根本没时间去消化 去经历这个过程之类的
people had not had time to like wrap their head around it, go through this process, whatever.
所以你懂的 各种事态不断升级
Uh, so, you know, we were like getting all of this escalating stuff and all these,
那些世界领导人都问 你能来见我们吗
like, world leaders were like, will you come meet us?
我们在想着做这做那 我当时就想…
We're like, you know, thinking about doing this and that. I was like, uh.
我觉得得由我或公司的人去 但那时公司还不大
I think if I or someone from the company, but at the time company was not very big.
所以大概只能我去 亲自露面跟人谈
So, I was like probably have to be me. Does not go like show up and talk to people.
我预感这事要变得很糟 我在考虑
I'd like a sense it's about to go very badly and I was thinking about doing,
安排一堆短途行程 但我讨厌长途飞行
like a bunch of short trips, but I hate long flights.
我讨厌倒时差 这些我都受不了
I hate jet lag. I had the whole thing.
所以我想 干脆短时间内一次性搞定
So I was like, I'm just gonna like get this over with in a short period of time.
Brian Chesky 建议我这么做
Um, Brian Chesky advised me to do it.
他为 Airbnb 做过类似的事
He had done something for Air B, similar for Air B, Bnb,
但他大概只跑了八个城市
but he had done like eight cities or something.
我就想 管他呢 拼了 干脆跑个三十 二十
And you're like, fuck it, we ball. Let's just do 30, 20.
我记得我们跑了28个国家 35天
I think we did 28 countries, 35 days.
我基本住在飞机上 特别奇怪
Uh, I like lived on an airplane. It was a very strange.
有床吗？有 挺舒服的
Did you have a bed? I had like a. Yeah, I was comfortable.
不过我坐的是经济舱 所以有点不一样
But yeah, I said, um, I fly coach, so it's a little bit different.
这比那强吧？强多了
This is better than that, right? This is a lot better than that.
但你懂的 出差还是很折磨
But like, you know, it's like travel still sucks.
你可以尽量弄得舒服 可你还是会
Like, you can make it as comfortable as you want and you still, like,
想念自己的床 自己的时区 自己的办公室之类的
miss your own bed and your own time zone and your office and whatever.
我学到的一点是 不管多少人
One thing that I've Learned is no matter how many people have, like,
有什么倒时差秘方 全是扯淡
these cures for jet lag, they're all bullshit.
就是很难受
Like, it just sucks.
你的大脑不喜欢 因为我去了太多地方
Your brain doesn't like it. I never in because I went to so many places.
我记得整趟最大的时差也就四小时
I think my biggest time zone change was four hours the whole trip.
大多时候是一次跳一个小时
And mostly it was like a one hour at a time hop.
所以时差没那么严重 我就是累坏了 很奇怪
So I wasn't that jet lagged. I was just like exhausted and it was very strange.
能这么快看遍世界还挺酷的
It was kind of cool to get to see the world so quickly
因为你真的能感受到那种文化差异
because you really do get a sense for like cultural differences
从一个地方到另一个地方 那些很微妙的差异
that are very subtle when you go from place to place.
但到最后 尤其是最后几天
But by the end of it, like the last few days I started,
那是一种很奇怪的 半睡半醒的状态
it was one of these like weird, you know, half asleep,
有点像做梦
half awake kind of somewhat dreams.
我开始有一种画面感 说不清
But I started having this like vision feeling, whatever,
觉得自己躺在小时候的床上
of being in my childhood bed.
有意思 这在之前和之后都没有过
Interesting. Which I never had before or since.
我会迷迷糊糊地醒来
But I would sort of like vaguely wake up
然后以为自己在小时候的房间 小时候的床上
and I would think I was in my childhood bed in my childhood room.
我就想 好吧 这是某种深层的 该回家了的信号
And I was like, okay, this is some, like, deep it's time to go home thing.
你的潜意识在反抗之类的 有意思
You're like, subconscious is fighting back or something like that. Interesting.
当你处于僵尸模式 还努力维持运转的时候
When you're in zombie mode and you're kind of like trying to function, I think, uh,
或者叫哥布林模式 随你喜欢
or goblin mode, whatever you prefer.
你会有什么变化？你哪里不一样了
How do you change? Like, what is different about you?
你是怎么决定继续撑下去的？我确实…
How do you decide to keep on going? I definitely.
到快结束的时候 我开始倒数还有几天能回家
Got to this point near the end where I was like counting down the days till I could be home.
因为每一天都是
Um, I was like, I, because each day was like, was like, you know,
14小时不停歇 而我不是个外向的人
14 hours of like non stop and I'm like not a extroverted person.
有时候我一天要见上百人
You know, I was meeting like hundreds of people a day in some cases.
到最后 紧张情绪缓和了些
Um, and like, tensions lowered by the end of it.
但一开始 整个世界都非常紧张 然后
But at the beginning, like, the world was like very nervous and, and then like,
我觉得后来它确实平静下来了
you know, I think once it just like it did calm down.
有一点帮了忙 那就是我很清楚
I think one thing that helped is it was clear that like,
我知道自己什么时候能回家
I knew when I was gonna get home
我知道之后还得再这么干一段时间
and I knew I was gonna have to do it again for a while.
后来我做过一些规模小点的
Um, I've done smaller ones since.
大概每年会来这么一两次
I probably do like something like that once or twice a year.
但我想说，我学到的一点是，我更愿意
But I was gonna say, like a thing I Learned is that I would much
把一堆国际出差集中在七到十天里搞定
rather put a bunch of international travel together in like a seven or 10 day chunk
而不是分散成一堆单日行程
than a bunch of one day trips spread out.
所以我一直都尽量这么安排
So I always do try to do it that way.
我觉得很多人高估了
Now, I think a lot of people overestimate the, like,
大多数行动所涉及的风险
risk involved in making most actions.
比如说，确实有很大风险，如果你只是
Like, there is a lot of risk if you're just, you know,
在 Robinhood 上买一堆看涨期权
buying a bunch of call options on Robin Hood,
但上飞机跑一趟这种事，风险其实小得多
but there's probably a lot less risk on getting on planes and stuff.
有哪些最典型的例子，你做的事情
What have been the best examples of times where you basically did something
在别人看来风险很大，但你知道或相信并不是
that seemed really risky to other people but you knew wasn't or you believed wasn't.
我想最明显的例子就是，我
I guess the obvious example would be like, I.
我一直极其坚定地大量购买算力
I was always extremely high conviction lost buying a lot of compute.
你见过那个梗吗？只要你怂，什么都是高风险
You ever seen the meme? Everything's high risk if you're a pussy?
挺好的梗
No good meme.
我花很多时间跟人聊，为什么他们觉得某个
Um, I spend a lot of time trying to talk to people about why they think a specific
决定是高风险还是低风险
decision is high risk or low risk.
我发现光是让人把它说出口，往往就能
And I have found that just getting people to speak about it out loud will often at
至少突破他们在理性上任一方向的卡点
least get through their intellectual blocks in either direction
因为人们通常总会往某个方向想偏
because people are usually wrong one way or the other.
情绪那部分不一定能解决
Not always the emotional part of it,
但有时候，如果你要在这种会议里想清楚
but sometimes also if you had to think through one of these meetings
有人坚决反对你想做的某个决定
where someone is like firmly against some decision that you want to do,
最有效的方式是怎么帮他们看到你看到的东西
what is the most effective way to kind of help them see what you see.
老实说，我觉得我不太擅长这个
I don't think I'm very good at this, to be honest.
我觉得正确的做法是花大量时间去真正解释清楚
I think like the right answer is to spend a lot of time really trying to explain it
把人带到那个认知上
and get people there.
我其实觉得我以前更擅长这个
And I actually think I used to be better at that.
现在生活太忙，我更多时候就是
And as life has gotten so busy, I'm more just like,
会烦躁、沮丧，或者直接说就这么定了，而我不
I get upset or frustrated or say this what we're gonna do and I don't,
我不觉得这是个好特质
I don't think it's like a positive trait
我想回到更多那种
and I would like to get back to more of the like.
咱们好好把它聊透
Let's really talk it through.
你说过你以前更难共事，大概是 2008、09、10 年
You said that you used to be much harder to work with, I don't know, 2008, 9, 10,
那前后，比现在难合作得多
somewhere around there than you are today.
我不知道别人会不会形容我很好合作
I don't know if people describe me as fun to work with,
我觉得是有意思、有效率、有野心
I like interesting to work with, like effective ambition,
非常聚焦使命，但日常上是不是真的好合作
raising like very mission focused, but like day to day like really fun to work with.
我觉得总体上我不是个特别有趣的人
I don't think I'm like a particularly fun person in general.
我觉得如果你自己乐在其中，这往往会传染
I feel like if you are having a good time, it's tends to be infectious.
我觉得如果你大体上做的是自己想做的事
And I think if you are generally working on things that you want to work on,
那本身就是一种享受
it is having a good time.
也许我错了
Uh, maybe I'm wrong.
你可以去问一堆跟我共事的人，我不是
I mean, you could go ask a bunch of people I work with. I'm not.
我不是，我觉得你不会听到一致的“很好合作”
I'm not. I don't. I don't think you would get like a resounding fun to work with.
可能不会是那种说法
Maybe not that language.
我觉得他们会说，能给出有创意的解决方案、新洞见
I think people would say stuff like creative solutions to problems, new insights,
有非常高的野心
like very high level of ambition,
让我做成了自己以为做不到的事，诸如此类
like got me to do something I didn't think I could do, that kind of thing.
通常会是什么样子，当你跟某人开会
What does it typically look like when you go into a meeting with someone
意识到他们野心不够
and you realize that they are not ambitious enough
而你需要去帮他们变得更有野心
and you need to try to help them become more ambitious.
你说这话时，我脑子里浮现的场景
The, the, the version of this that came to mind when you were saying
就像我和新一批 YC 创始人第一次办公时间的谈话
that was like first office hours I would have with new YC founders and.
你随便找个在美国大公司干过的人，或者
You take average person who's worked in corporate America or, you know,
在大科技公司干了几年，他们的野心量级
at a big tech company for a few years and the level of ambition scaled.
思维、自信，随便哪样，都低得离谱。糟透了，糟透了
Thinking, self belief, whatever, it's just catastrophically low. Horrible, horrible.
你会发现这个人一辈子从来没有过没有老板的时候
And you realize that like this person has never not had a boss in their life.
他们从来都有个家长、老师、经理之类的
They have never not had a parent or a teacher or a manager or whatever
会告诉他们该做什么、能做什么
that kind of would tell them what to do or what they were allowed to do or whatever.
而且他们还会因为太有创意、想要太多而受到惩罚
And they also kind of got punished for being too creative or wanting too much or
或者因为想得太大、太有野心
thinking too big or too ambitious, whatever.
大多数国家或文化都有形容野心太大的说法
Like the most countries or cultures have some sort of phrase for being too ambitious,
基本上就是"高罂粟花综合征"
basically tall Poppy syndrome.
这是其中一种
That's one.
你会意识到这在人心里扎得多深，他们从小就听到这些
Um, and you realize, like how deep this is in people and that they like heard it
父母对他们说、老师对他们说、朋友对他们说
and their parents said it to them, their teachers said to them or friends with them,
从他们还很小的时候
whatever, from when they were, like.
很小的时候就开始了
Quite little.
让人们摆脱那种思维方式，真的需要时间
And getting people to just like not think that way, take some real time.
让一个人从不相信自己到相信自己
What's the most effective path to get someone from not believing in themselves to
最有效的路径是什么
believing in themselves?
我觉得是不断的小胜利，做到你原以为做不到的事
I think small repeated wins, like you do something you didn't think you could do or
或者你去尝试一件感觉
you kind of try something that felt, you know,
太有野心、期望太高的事，结果成了，你就想，好吧
too ambitious or too high expectation and it works and you're so, okay,
那我再试一次
I'll try it again.
你会像 Steve Jobs 那样吗，如果有人担心
Do you do anything like Steve Jobs where he would like, if someone was worried,
他会盯着人家的眼睛——不，完全没有那种
he would like stare into their eyes and get no, nothing like that.
我不觉得，就是"你能做到"
I don't think so. It's like you can do it.
我不是那种，我不做励志演讲
I, I don't, I don't, I'm not like an ins. I don't do inspirational speeches.
我不搞那种煽情的东西，完全不
I don't, I don't do like the hearts to none of that.
你最喜欢的策略游戏是什么
What's your favorite strategy game?
我好久没玩过游戏了，除了跟朋友的扑克夜
I have not played a game other than like my poker night with friends in so long.
我倒希望我玩过
Uh, I wish I had.
那我只能说扑克吧，但我挺怀念那些好玩的桌游
I guess I'll have to say poker, but I, uh, I miss, like, great board games.
你最喜欢的桌游是什么
What was your favorite board game?
没有哪一款桌游是我会想着，我想一遍又一遍
There's like no one board game where I'd be like, I want to play that, like,
反复去玩的
again and again.
我不是那种会说
I don't have, like, a, like, I'm not, like, someone who's like,
Catan 是史上最好的桌游之类的人，但它们都很好玩
Catan is the best board game of all time or whatever, but they're all fun.
好玩是因为它们是新的，你得
And they're fun because they're like new and you have to, like,
去搞清楚一套新的挑战、规则和一切
figure out a new set of challenges and rules and everything else
当你思考商业世界时
when you're thinking about the business world.
我觉得你建公司的方式，跟几乎所有人都不一样
I think you build your company differently than almost anyone else is able to build
别人能建、也愿意建的方式
companies, is willing to build companies.
是什么让你能做到这点？其实每家大公司都很不一样
What allows you to do that? Actually, every big company is pretty different.
我不觉得这是什么独特的事
I don't think this is a unique thing.
如果你列出最大的20家科技公司
I think just like if you make a list of the 20 biggest tech companies or whatever,
它们在战略上彼此差异大得惊人
they're all like shockingly different from each other in terms of their strategy
在运作方式和文化上也是
and how they operate and their culture.
我觉得我们跟所有人都很不一样
And I think we are quite different than everybody else,
但这算不上什么深刻洞见。你觉得你的超能力是什么
but that's not a deep insight. What do you think you're like superpower is?
我觉得我们做得很好的一点，是对某件事有原则性的坚定信念
I think we did a really good job of a principled conviction on something
一件没人相信的事，尽管它本该是显而易见该相信的
that no one else believed, even though it was the obvious thing one should believe,
然后把所有的部分和人才拼到一起
and then putting together all of the pieces and the talent around
围绕它，让它真正发生
that to sort of make it happen.
是什么让你拥有那种别人没有的信念
What allowed you to kind of have that conviction that where other people just didn't?
我想过很多次这个问题
Um, I have thought about this a lot.
我不知道
I do not know.
对我们所有人来说都太显而易见了，我更担心的是
It seemed so clearly obvious is to all of us that I was more worried
我们是不是在自欺欺人，而不是别人都错了
that we were drinking our own Kool Aid than everybody else was wrong.
但事后看来，我们显然是对的
But with the benefit of hindsight, we were clearly right.
我不理解那种深层的心理障碍
And I don't understand the like deep mental block
和所有人缺乏信念这件事，非常奇怪。我
and lack of conviction from everybody else. It's very strange. I. I have.
我花了很多时间想搞懂这件事
I have spent a lot of time trying to understand this.
在你那番"探寻为什么"的过程中，找到解释了吗
Did you find any explanation in your, you know, man's search for why or no?
我是说，有些显而易见的因素，比如从众思维之类的
Um, I mean, there's all the obvious stuff about, like, group think and, like,
重大变革不是随时都会到来的
the big transformations just come,
它们并不常来，指数曲线也一样
don't come along that often and exponential curves don't.
它不会一直那么强、那么频繁地起作用，但你懂的
Stay powerful for so long, for so often, but like, you know,
也许在 2016 到 2018 年之间，我们得非常走运
maybe between 2016 and 2018, we had to get really lucky.
而且需要极大的信念
And it required like a lot of great belief.
但到了 2019 年，尤其是 2020 年，我们本来根本不该还存在
But then by 2019, certainly by 2020, we shouldn't have really gotten to exist.
Google 本该一骑绝尘的 对
Google should have just run away with it. Yeah.
我记得 Jeff Bezos 把它称为一个商业奇迹，他们做出了 AWS
I think Jeff Bezos called it like a business miracle that they built AWS
而且大约七年里都没有像样的竞争
and then didn't have any serious competition for like seven years.
我觉得 OpenAI 也算是另一个商业奇迹
And I feel like OpenAI is like another business miracle.
这里显然揭示了大公司为什么会变得僵化
There's clearly something here about why big companies get sclerotic
变得墨守成规，而这在很多方面也帮了它们
and set in their ways and it helps them in a lot of ways too.
但这真的很棒 我觉得这是好事
But this is like, I mean, this is wonderful. I think it's great that.
大公司不会永远是唯一的主导力量 否则会很糟糕
The big companies don't stay the only dominant forces forever. That'd be really bad.
但显然有某种机制，让这些商业奇迹会发生
Um, but there's clearly something where these business miracles happen
而它们本不该发生
and they shouldn't.
是这样吗 还是说它们本该发生
Is that right? Or should they?
我觉得它们发生对世界是好事 对
Well, I think it's great for the world that they do. Right.
但要回到 2019 年去解释，为什么那些拥有海量资本和人才的巨头
But to go back and explain in 2019 why OpenAI was like allowed by the Giants with
会允许 OpenAI 做成我们做到的这些事
huge amounts of capital and talent and everything else to do what we've done.
这真的很难解释
It's like hard to explain.
Microsoft 为什么给你们投钱
Why did Microsoft give you the money?
这个我觉得更好解释
Um, that I think is easier to explain,
就是 Google 有 DeepMind，而 Microsoft 没有一个 AI 的押注
which is Google had deep mind and Microsoft did not have an AI bet.
你知道，大公司会觉得自己应该在所有主要技术领域
And you know, big companies feel like they should have something in play in all of
都要有一手布局
the major areas of technology.
是不是有点像，他们知道这会很大
Was it kind of like they think it's going to be big,
但又低估了它到底能有多大
but then underestimated how big it would be?
我觉得这对他们来说非常划算
I think it's been like great for them.
我不知道我们是给 Microsoft 增加了一万亿
I don't know if we've added one trillion,
还是两万亿美元的市值，或者别的数字
two trillion dollars or whatever of market cap to Microsoft,
但我觉得数额很大
but I think it's been a lot.
而且我觉得他们获得了了不起的技术和云业务增长
Um, and I think they have gotten incredible technology and cloud growth
而且还会持续下去
and will continue to.
所以是的，我相信它比我当初预想的还要大
So yeah, I'm sure it's bigger than I thought it was going to be,
但我觉得他们下了个好赌注，而且做得非常好
but I think they made a good bet and have done super well with it.
我为此很高兴 OpenAI 经历过不同的版本
And I'm very happy about that. There's been different versions of OpenAI.
第一个是研究实验室 下一个是产品公司
The first one was the research lab. Next one was the product company.
你说过你们是把产品公司硬拼到研究实验室上的
And you kind of said that like you bolted on the product company onto the research
这跟大多数公司的做法正好相反
lab, which is the exact opposite of what most companies do.
而现在你们基本上要变成一家巨型基础设施公司
And now you're basically gonna be like a massive infrastructure company
OpenAI 几乎所有的价值都将来自这种低利润的
and like almost all the value from OpenAI is just gonna come from this like low
基础设施
margin infrastructure.
然后你还说，基本上
And then you also said that basically,
为了过渡到这项业务的下一个阶段
in order to transition into the next phase of this business,
你大脑天生的运作方式
it's not necessarily something the way
未必天然适合在那种模式下运作
that your brain works is naturally like designed to operate in that kind of model.
你必须改变什么 那下一阶段的业务又是什么
What do you have to change? And like what is that next phase of the business?
我不回答这个，因为我觉得这现在进入了一个
I don't answer this because I don't like, I think this is now a getting into like a,
我们还没准备好谈论的方向
like a direction we're not quite ready to talk about.
但我对下一个阶段非常期待
But, uh, I am very excited for the next phase
而且我觉得我想清楚了，怎么把我非常擅长
and I think I figured out how to align something that I am very good at
也非常热爱的东西，跟接下来的方向对齐
and very passionate about with what will be the next.
也就是我们接下来十倍、百倍的增长
Like 10 or hundred x of our growth.
那从“研究实验室负责人 Sam”到“产品公司负责人 Sam”的转变是怎样的
So how did the transition of Sam the research lab head to Sam the product company head?
那是什么样的 对你来说最大的转变是什么
Like what was that? What were the biggest transitions for you on that?
我是说，整件事完全不一样
I mean, that the whole thing was just extremely different.
感觉就像是两份几乎毫不相干的工作
Like it has felt like two almost completely unrelated jobs.
也不能说
And it's not quite to say, like,
我先做完一份，现在做另一份
I did one and now I do the other
因为我还得负责研究实验室
because I'm also still responsible for the research lab.
但它们几乎是两回事
Um, but they are almost separate things
而且管研究实验室完全没有让我为做产品公司做好准备
and definitely running the research lab did not prepare me for running the product
一点都没有
company in really any way.
那 YC 的经历有没有让你更有准备
Did the YC experience prepare you more?
我看过很多人不得不去扩张大公司
Um, like I had watched a lot of people have to scale big companies.
终于自己坐上驾驶座，是不是很爽？不
Was it fun to kind of like finally get in the driver seat? No.
ChatGPT 发布后的第五天，我们突破了 100 万用户
I the fifth day after ChatGPT launch was the day we crossed 1 million users
我看着它第一天涨上去，下午又掉下来
and I had like watched it go up the first day and then come down in the afternoon
第二天又涨到更高的峰值
and then go up the second day to a higher peak.
然后掉下来，第三天涨到更高峰值，再掉下来
And then come down, go up the third day to a higher peak and then come down.
每一天，研究员们都说
And each of these days, the researchers were like, oh,
那不过是一阵疯狂的昙花一现的公关效应
that was some crazy flash in the pan PR thing.
这就要过去了，你知道那不会持续
This is, like over. And you know that's not gonna happen.
但我在 YC 见得够多，我知道当一样东西那样增长时
And I had seen enough at YC that I knew that when something was growing like that,
完全是自然增长的，对我来说这有着所有那种特征
completely organically, it, this had all of the spectral signature to me of
就是一件真正会发生的事
something that is like was gonna happen.
然后第五天，它突破了 100 万用户，我回到家
And then on the fifth day, it crossed a million users and I came home and
那一刻我才真正意识到
that was when it really hit me that, like,
我们即将变成一家公司，而且会走得非常快
we were about to become a company and it was gonna go very fast
会变得很疯狂
and it was gonna be a crazy like a like.
我们很快就会变成一家大公司
We were just gonna turn into like a big company real quick.
我见过这些创始人经历过什么
And I had watched what these founders went through.
我回到家，Ali 说，我看到你们突破 100 万用户了
And I came home and Ali was like, oh, I saw that you crossed a million users.
恭喜。我说，你根本不知道这有多糟
Congratulations. I was like, you have no idea how bad this is.
你根本不知道接下来会发生什么
You have no idea what's about to happen.
这不只是对我糟，对你也糟
It's not just bad for me. It's bad for you, too.
我们本来过着安静美好的生活，真的很棒
Like we have this nice quiet life, you know, it's really wonderful.
现在它就要像被大炮轰出去一样，后来确实如此
It's about to like kind of go through a cannon and that is what happened.
但那是一个非常突然的转变
But it was like a very abrupt transition.
我知道它会来，我也看过别人经历过
I knew it was gonna come and I had watched other people go through it,
我知道那不是什么愉快的体验，但我想，好吧
and I knew that it was like not a pleasant experience, but I was like, well,
我们要被大炮发射出去了
we're being shot out of the cannon.
开始吧
Here we go.
如果你知道这终究会发生，你是不是下意识里
Were you like subconsciously just like preparing yourself for years if you know
已经为此准备了好几年
that this is eventually going to happen
等到智能足够强大时
and the intelligence is gonna get good enough where like,
会出现一个神奇的产品。我的看法是
there will be a magical product. My take on it is that I.
我确实知道它总有一天会发生，只是不知道什么时候
Actually knew it was gonna happen at some point. I had no idea when.
当然，我也不知道那会是那个时刻
I didn't know that was gonna be the moment, of course.
但我决定假装
Um, but that I had decided to pretend to,
对自己假装，我成功地骗了自己，装作这不会发生
to myself and I had successfully deluded myself into a sort of acting like it wasn't gonna happen.
说真的，管研究实验室是最酷、最有意思
Um, truly running the research lab was the coolest, most fun,
我能想象到的最棒的工作和生活方式
most amazing job and lifestyle setup I could possibly have imagined.
怎么说
How so?
我是说，那完全没有压力
I mean, you were like, it's not stressful at all.
它在智识上极其令人满足
Uh, it was intellectually incredibly satisfying.
那是一群最聪明的人，做着可能是最重要的工作
It was the smartest group of people with probably the most important work
过去一个世纪，甚至更久，我也说不好
that has happened in like, the last century, maybe longer, I don't know.
而我坐在最前排的位置
And I had this, like, front row seat and.
那是几代人才遇一次的时刻，简直难以置信
Like that was a once in many generations moment. It was unbelievable.
那是最酷的事
It was the coolest thing.
你们现在还在经历那种增长吗
Are you guys experiencing that same kind of growth?
我一直在 X 上看到 TBO 发帖，基本上就是又一次重置
You know, I keep on seeing TBO post on Twitter that basically here's another reset,
又一次重置
here's another reset.
你们又看到那种类似 ChatGPT 的情况了吗？完全是
Are you seeing that same like chat GPT esque experience again? Totally.
我觉得到目前为止出现了两种巨大的产品形态和相应的增长
Um, I think there have been two giant form factors and associated growth so far.
一种是聊天机器人，然后是编程 agents
There was the sort of chatbots and then the coding agents,
而编程 agents 正彻底爆发
and the coding agents are just going totally nuts.
我觉得很快会有第三种
There will be a third one soon, I think,
也就是这种持续存在的 agents、幕僚长
which will be this idea of this sort of persistent agents, chiefs of staffs,
同事、伙伴，随便你怎么叫它们
co workers, colleagues, whatever we call them.
我觉得这会很快到来
And that'll, and you know, I think that'll come pretty soon.
我们会很快经历这几波浪潮中的第三波
So we're gonna go through like the third of these waves pretty fast.
很久以前，好像是去年八月
So a long time ago, apparently in August last year,
我看到你发了条推文，心里想
I saw you tweet something and I thought to myself,
这对声誉可没好处。说说吧，你为什么那么做
this is not gonna help the reputation. Let's see why. Why did you do that?
首先，我特别喜欢电影里那一幕，Death Star（死星）从超空间里
Well, first of all, I love that scene from the movie like the Death Star is coming
冒出来，配上那段戏剧性的音乐，特别棒
out of hyperspace and there's this dramatic music and it's like a great,
那是个很棒的场景
it's like a great scene.
我当时觉得挺好笑的，就像
Um, I thought it was a funny, like I was, it was like, you know,
我在刷 Twitter
I was scrolling Twitter.
好像是深夜，我记不太清了
I think it was late at night. I don't really remember.
阴谋论就是这么来的，你就像
This is where the conspiracy theories happen. Like you're, you're like,
你在这儿火上浇油
you're feeding the fire here.
我只是觉得，当时它逗到我了
I just thought it was, it amused me at the time.
说实话，那条推文其实不算好，我得说清楚
There was like, it was, I don't know, it was not a great tweet, to be honest, to be clear.
我倒觉得挺好的。我觉得很好笑，很好笑
Uh, I actually thought it was great. I thought it was funny. I thought it was funny.
我记得我当时觉得很好笑，对
I think I thought it was funny. Yeah.
我确实觉得这世界越来越像那样
Um, I do feel like this is more and more what the world feels like.
对，对，好
Uh, yes. Uh, yes. Okay.
对，这是个好梗
Yes, that's a good, that's a good meme.
有人这样解释 OpenAI 面临的营销挑战
The way that somebody explained kind of the marketing challenge for OpenAI
以及整个行业的挑战，第一
and the industry in general is, No. 1,
我们快要造出需要向世界解释的东西了
we are close to creating what we need to explain in the world.
第一，我们快要造出一个能实现任何愿望的精灵
No. 1, we are close to creating a genie that can grant any wish.
第二，我们要确保最初的愿望广泛造福人类
No.2, we are going to make sure that our first wishes broadly benefit humanity
让世界走到这样一个地步
and that we kind of get the world to a place
让更多人能许下更多愿望
where a lot more people get to have a lot more witches wishes.
还有第
And No..
三，你能许下的愿望空间无比广阔、充满创造力
3, the space of what you can wish for is incredibly big and creative
而且会很令人兴奋
and it'll be quite exciting to, like,
结合真正的人类价值观和偏好去搞清楚这一点
figure that out with real sort of human values and preferences.
但我觉得还有第四点，正是这个
But, but I think there's a fourth thing too, which is exactly that.
你开始许愿，计算机把它们实现了，然后你会想
You start making these wishes, the computer grants them, and then you're like,
我没想到那真能成
I didn't think that was gonna work.
对，接下来呢？那是种奇怪的感觉
Yeah, what now? It's a weird feeling.
对，就像那个难题，人们花了大概
Yeah, it's just like the problem where I guess, you know, people spent, like,
一百年想去推翻某个东西
100 years trying to disprove some.
是 Jacobian 吗？对，对，就那个
Was it Jacobian? Yeah. Yeah. This thing.
然后有个人直接问了 Claude，大概
And then some guy just asked Claude and it was like, I don't know,
几天之内就搞定了之类的
within a few days or something like this.
所以我觉得未来会有很多很棒的工作
So I'm, I'm, I'm, I think there's gonna be lots of great jobs in the future.
我真这么认为
I really do.
我觉得我们会有很多智识上的满足感
I think we're gonna have lots of intellectual fulfillment
而且大多数工作的适应程度会超出你的预期
and I think most jobs are going to adapt more than it seems like they should.
但数学，我觉得是个很重要的例子，值得我们现在
But math, I think, is a very important example of something for us to study very
密切研究，它可能不会朝那个方向走
closely right now of something that may not go that way.
事实上，我会说它很可能不会那样
In fact, I would say probably won't go that way.
看起来即便系统越来越强
It seems like even as the systems get better and better,
我认识的人里，没有一个变得更闲
the people that I know that like no one is less busy.
大家都更忙了
Everyone is more busy.
大家都在做更多事，除了那些说"哦，我
Everyone's just doing more stuff except for the people that are like, oh, I,
我用掉了一万亿个 token"的人，我特别喜欢
I spent a trillion tokens, uh, and like, what have, I love this, uh,
我看到的那个说法，有人说，我花了
thing that I saw where someone said, like, I spent.
用掉了多到离谱的 token
You know, ungodly numbers of tokens.
然后有人说，那你怎么没更成功呢
And then someone said, why aren't you more successful, you know,
长久以来，科技一直在向人们承诺，他们会工作更少
technology for a long time has been promising people that they're gonna work less
拥有大把闲暇时间
and they're gonna have all this leisure.
而它确实朝那个方向走了，我觉得人们确实如此
And it has gone in that direction, like I think people do.
比历史上很多时期都有更多闲暇时间
Have more time for leisure than they had at many previous points in history
生活质量在很多方面也更高
and a higher quality of life in many ways.
但不知为何，社会层面从没实现过每周工作四小时的承诺
But somehow we never get the promise of the four hour work week at mass scale in society.
我也不指望 AI 会改变这一点
And I don't expect AI to change that.
显然社会对很多人来说是失灵的，如果更多的生产力增益
Clearly society is not working for a lot of people and more productivity gains
真正落到普通人身上，那会是件好事
that actually accrued to people would be a great thing.
我猜会的，我猜这会发生
And I suspect they will. I suspect that will happen.
但我真正欣赏人类的一点是，我们的期望会不断提高
But I think that I really admire about people is our expectations go up.
我们总想要更多，会想出新东西为彼此去创造
We always want more. We think of new things to do to create for each other,
也为自己去追求
to want for ourselves.
而且这就像一场相对的游戏
And we, you know, it's like a, it's like a relative game.
人们非常在意自己相对于别人过得怎么样
People are like very focused on how they're doing relative to other people.
所以是这种竞争在驱动经济，还有那种
And so the competition that drives the economy and the kind of, I think the, the,
想对他人有用的美好愿望
the very wonderful desires about wanting to be useful to other people
想创造点什么、想服务他人
and create something and be of service.
这一整套东西，我觉得会一直延续下去
And that whole cluster, I expect that to keep going.
我觉得在超级智能到来之后的世界里
And I think we're all gonna be much busier than we thought we were supposed to be in
我们都会比想象中忙得多
a post super intelligence world.
我们还是会抱怨，但心里其实是开心的
And we're still gonna complain about it, but secretly we're gonna be happy.
你觉得地位游戏会怎么变化，当我们的直接投入
How do you think the status games change as less
越来越少地和价值创造相关时
and less of our direct input is correlated with like value creation?
我不觉得，我不觉得那会感觉像我们的直接付出
I don't. I don't think it will feel at all like our direct,
就是我们所珍视的东西
like the things that we value.
我猜会是那些非常人性化的东西
I suspect will be things that are like very human.
比如说为别人做饭
But like one thing is like cooking for people.
你并没有为世界创造多少价值，但它表达了爱
You're not like creating a bunch of value in the world, but it like shows love.
你在其中创造了价值
You are creating value in that.
就是那些体验
It's like those are the experiences
也许在传统意义上你没有创造经济价值
that you're not creating like economic value in the maybe traditional sense.
呃，为别人做饭就是个很好的例子
Um, cooking for people is a great example.
我猜在机器人能把饭做得很好之后很久
I suspect that people cooking and eating together will remain important long
人们一起做饭、一起吃饭仍然会很重要
after robots can do a great job cooking food.
你觉得一个好的判断标准是不是差不多就是那些最伟大的作品
Do you think that a good heuristic would almost be like the greatest works of the
那些流传最久的作品
the longest surviving works.
比如说《圣经》
So let's say the Bible for example,
它很可能一千年后仍然有影响力
odds are it's still gonna be impactful like 1,000 years from now
因为它在过去两千年里一直有影响力
because it's been impactful for the past 2,000 years so far.
你觉得如果要推演出人类仍然会在意的东西
Do you think that if you had to like extrapolate out what are the things
会不会就是那些最原始、最古早的东西
that humans are still gonna care about, it's like, what is the most primal, earliest thing?
你知道的，我们热爱冒险，热爱一场好的征程
You know, we love adventure. We love a good quest.
是的，我觉得跟进化生物学对着干，通常是笔坏赌注，所以我会
Yeah, I think betting against evolutionary biology is, like, usually a bad bet. Yeah. And so I would.
我会假设那些东西会延续下去
I would assume those things continue.
你上一次意识到自己
When was the last time that you realized
还不够有野心，是什么时候
that you weren't like being ambitious enough?
我是说，我在算力投入上明显严重低估了
I mean, I definitely badly undershot on the compute investments.
如果一开始就有正确的思维模型，你能预见到吗
Could you have known going in with the right mental model?
能，但我大概是被金融市场之类的东西吓退了，我也说不清
Yes, but I got like psyched out by the financial markets or something. I don't know.
那显然是个错误
That was clearly a mistake.
以后你怎么纠正这一点
How do you correct that in the future?
我是说，希望我能从中吸取教训，然后再犯些新错误
Well, I mean, hopefully I'll learn from it and I'll make some new mistakes,
但那个错误我不会再犯
but I won't make that one again.
在算力这边，这差不多是有史以来最大的基础设施项目
On the compute side, this is kind of like the biggest infrastructure project of
或者即将成为最大的
maybe all time or is about to be.
是的
Yeah.
你会不会试着在 OpenAI 内部把所有环节垂直整合起来
Are you gonna try and like vertically integrate under opening eyes hood everything
从发电到 token 生成
from like power generation to like token generation to, you know,
再到为 ChatGPT 或 Codex 里的某个用户提供服务之类的
serving some person in ChatGPT or Codex or something like
还是你会去找一堆合作伙伴
that or are you gonna try and have a bunch of partners?
显然，我们不会真的想把一切都放在 OpenAI 内部做
We're not literally gonna try to do it all inside of OpenAI, obviously,
但我们会努力把供应链运转得比目前更好
but we will try to do a better job of a well functioning supply chain than we have done so far.
比如说 我们把芯片设计和模型设计放到了一起
Like you know, we we have brought chip design and model design together and
效果很好
that's been good.
我觉得我们不需要用同样的方式把电子生产也整合进来
I don't think we need to bring like electron production together in the same way
因为那更像是一种大宗商品
because that's more of a commodity.
不过 当你真正去想产生智能所需的整条供应链
Uh, however, I am when you really think about the whole supply chain
我会说 相对来说
that has to come together to produce intelligence, I would say there is relatively.
太多精力放在能产出更好算法的算法上
Too much focus on algorithms that create.
而放在能造出更多数据中心的
Better algorithms and not enough focus on data centers
数据中心上的精力不够
that can create more data centers,
在一个有机器人、真正自动化供应链的世界里
which in a world of robots and a truly automated supply chain,
你完全可以想象这样做 你可以用一个数据中心的思考能力
you can totally imagine doing, you can like spend a data center's thinking power to
去驱动一队机器人 造出更多数据中心的副本
drive a fleet of robots to make more copies of the data center.
这可能是件非常美妙的事
And that's probably a very wonderful thing to do.
相对于那份算力的其他用途
Uh, relative to other uses of that compute,
如果我们对那些额外算力最终能解锁什么判断正确的话
if we're right about what that additional compute will eventually unlock,
你有多少时间花在思考怎样成功设计出
how much of your time is spent thinking about how to like successfully design
那个全机器人、端到端的未来
that fully robot end to end future
几乎没时间花在思考上，几乎全都投入执行
where Intel almost no time spent thinking about almost all goes into like execution,
因为这个想法很显而易见 它非常
like the idea that's a very obvious idea. It's very.
简单 你可以相对快地说出
Easy. You can like kind of relatively quickly say,
需要拼在一起的都有哪些部分
here's the pieces that need to come together.
但要让整台机器、所有那些公司协同运转起来
But then to like get that whole machinery and all those companies working together,
这里面没有大想法的光环 也不是去
um, that, that, you know, none of the glory of the big idea and trying to, like,
思考那些宏大的念头 而是
think the big thoughts, but, like.
大量的埋头苦干 当你想到执行时
A lot of grinding when you think of like execution,
它对你来说通常意味着什么 没有什么典型可言
what does that typically mean for you? Not there's no typical there like the.
我是说 真要说有的话 就是你只是
I mean, to the degree that there is, it's that you just like,
做这个问题里需要的任何一步 想办法让它实现
do whatever step is required in the problem to figure out how to make it happen.
但你知道 搞清楚怎么为新晶圆厂建设融资
But, you know, figuring out how to like finance new fab build out is very different
和搞清楚怎么组建一支出色的芯片设计团队
than figuring out how to get a great chip design team together
再让他们和研究团队协作
and then get them to work with the research team
然后真正让供应链顺畅运转 是非常不同的
and then actually get the supply chain running well.
就像
Like.
每一件都是完全不同的做法
Each of those is like a very different approach.
我知道 Brian Chesky 会做的一件事 就是他会毫不脸红地
One thing that I know that Brian Chesky does is he talks about like shamelessly
去找到任何一件事上的那个专家
trying to find whoever the expert is and any given thing
然后直接去问他心里的任何问题
and then basically just go ask them whatever question he has
如果他想快速上手某件事
if he's trying to come up to speed on something.
你做这种事的流程是什么
What is your process for doing something like.
如果是件你需要在很短时间内变精通的新事物
That if it's something new that you need to become good at in a very rapid period of time.
肯定是找到专家跟他们聊 尽可能多读
Definitely finding the experts and talking to them, reading as much as I can.
我没有什么特别厉害的 我没有什么
I don't have a lot of, like, great. I don't have a lot of, like,
新奇的策略
novel strategies here.
我一直非常感激
I've always been really grateful
也很惊喜地发现 只要你开口 专家们有多愿意帮人
and pleasantly surprised by how much experts are willing to help people if they ask.
这是人性中很美好的一点
It's like a very nice thing about humanity.
我听你说过一句话：应该总是开口要你想要的
One thing I've heard you say is you should always ask for what you want
因为你不会每次都得到 但有时候你会
because not all the time you get it, but sometimes you do.
有时候你会 而当你得到时 神奇的事就会发生
Sometimes you do. And when you do, amazing things can happen.
上一次你开口要一件
When was the last time that you asked for something
在别人看来绝对疯狂的事 而且真拿到了 是什么时候
that would seem absolutely insane to someone else and you got it.
其实是最近有一次我上了一架飞机 我现在还不能说 但
Actually, it was this recent time I got on a plane that I still can't talk about, but it.
好 往前再倒一个
Okay, go back one more.
倒回一个你能说的
Go back one more that you can talk about.
我是说 某种意义上 Codex 就是一个例子
I mean, in some sense, Codex was an example of this.
这不是最近的一个 但我觉得它很有启发性
Like, this is not the most recent one, but it was one that I think it's instructive.
我们当时远远落后于 Claude Code
Um, we were way behind Cloud Code
想用一个编程应用去打败他们 看起来像是一场疯狂的自杀式任务
and it seemed like a kind of crazy kamikaze mission to try to beat them with a coding app.
而你知道 共识是这种事从来不会成功
And you know, the like the consensus is that this kind of thing never works
你就该往下一件事走
and you just move on to the next one.
但你知道，这几乎是白费力气
But, you know, it's like a fool's errand to try to like,
想在别人已经占据势头的产品品类里胜出
win when someone else already has momentum in a particular product category.
但我们觉得这件事真的很重要，就找了个团队去做
But we decided we thought it was really important, we asked a team to do it.
他们做出了实打实、令人难以置信的成绩
They performed a legitimate, like unbelievable,
那种在商业史上都极为罕见的事
very rare in the history of business thing.
现在它是我认识的大多数顶尖程序员都在用的
And now it is the product that most of and model that most of the best coders
产品和模型
that I know use.
那当时感觉像是不可能的事，但如果我们没对团队说
Um, and that felt like an impossible thing, but if we hadn't asked the team, like,
嘿，我们有个非常重要但极其艰难的任务交给你们
hey, we have a really important but extremely hard mission for you.
这事根本不会发生
Just wouldn't have happened.
你为什么做那个决定？为什么不干脆放弃
Why did you make that decision? Why didn't you just give up?
因为它感觉属于那种
Because it felt like one of these.
少数几个会迅速成型的高度战略性领域
Few very strategic areas that was gonna happen very quickly.
而编程对 RSI 太重要了
And coding is so important to RSI,
更别提它的经济价值，我们就是
to say nothing of the economic value that we just didn't,
它感觉不像是我们能放弃的东西
it didn't feel like one we could give up on.
在 YC，你基本上抓住了那个使命最纯粹的版本
At YC, you basically had the most distilled version of what the mission was,
就是努力增加世界上的创新总量
is just trying to increase the amount of innovation in the world.
我的直觉是，如果你真去想为什么你决定去做
My hunch is that if you actually like thought about why did you decide to go work on
OpenAI 而不是留在 YC，你几乎可以论证
OpenAI instead of YC, you could almost make the argument
你在增加世界创新总量上能产生更大的影响
that you could just have a bigger impact on increasing the amount of innovation in
就是通过做这件事
the world through working on.
当时并没有想得那么理性化，就只是
It wasn't that intellectualized at the time, it was just like.
我这一辈子多少都知道
I kind of knew that my whole life.
我想做 AI，我也多少知道
I wanted to work on AI and I kind of knew
它会是我这辈子能接触到的最重要的事
that it would be the most important thing I could ever touch.
对我来说这就是热爱，我确实觉得它会非常重要
Like for me it was like my passion. I just, and I did think it'd be really important.
我就是想做。最初那几周是什么样的
I just wanted to do it. What were those first few weeks like?
我知道有过这么一段，我不知道你会不会把它叫作集训营
I know that there was this, I, I don't know if you'd describe it as a camp,
但基本上大家就是聚在一起搞了个类似闭关的活动
but people just basically like all got together on some kind of retreat
那时候都还没打算做成一家公司，我觉得就只是
and it wasn't even like, meant to be a company at the time. I think it was just like, like.
一旦开始的那最初几周，对，不，我们
The first few weeks, once we started, yeah. No, we were,
我们在 Greg Brockman 的公寓里
we were in Greg Brockman's apartment.
对，大概就我们十个人、十二个人
Yes. Um, and there were maybe like 10 of us, 12 of us.
为了把它启动起来，之前做了那么多准备
And, you know, it had been all of this work to get it going.
然后有一天我们都到了
And then we showed up one day.
第一天，差不多是一月吧
The first day I was like, you know, January, something like that.
我就想，好，我们到齐了，接下来干什么
And I was like, so here we are. What are we gonna do?
我们该弄块白板
We should get a whiteboard.
我们该开始聊想法
We should start talking about ideas.
也许我们该写点论文
Maybe we should write papers.
然后我心里想，哦，操，我们都干了些什么
And I had this like, oh, fuck, what have we done?
那真是个特别疯狂的时刻
Like, it was like a really crazy moment.
你当时是不是已经向全世界宣布了
Um, had you already like, committed to the world
也向一大堆人说了，我们要做这个，但花了
and a whole bunch of other people like, we're doing this, but it took,
花了好几年才真正找到状态
it took a couple of years to like really get our groove
才想清楚我们到底要做什么
and figure out what we're gonna do.
那真的不是，我是说，我们知道我们想搞清楚怎么造出 AI
Just it was not, I mean, we knew that we wanted to like figure out how to build AI,
但除此之外，天哪，真的很不清晰
but beyond that, man, really unclear.
当你处在这种像在树林里摸索前行的阶段，你知道的
When you're in the like stumbling through the woods phase of this type of, you know,
这种曼哈顿计划式的项目，你怎么最高效地在树林里摸索
Manhattan Project, how do you most efficiently just stumble through the trees to
快速搞清楚哪些事不该做
rapidly figure out what not to work on?
我是说，如果某件事行不通，你又没主意了，你可以砍掉它
I mean, if something is not working and you run out of ideas, you can kill it.
那反而算容易的
That's kind of easier.
真正难的是，当某件事进展得特别好时
The really hard thing is when something is working super well,
你什么时候决定砍掉其他东西，让它做得更好
when do you decide to kill the other things to make it work even better?
OpenAI 历史上有过很多相当重要的时刻
So there have been a lot of quite important moments in Opening Eyes history
那时某件事开始真正奏效
where one thing started to really work
我们砍掉其他好东西，让最好的那件事做得更好
and we killed other good things to make the best thing work better.
所以当 GPT-3 开始奏效时，我们关停了像机器人这样的项目
So when GPT 3 started to work, we shut down things like robotics,
一些我们真正兴奋的东西，就为了全力专注这件事
stuff that we're really excited about to really focus on this.
后来最近编程 agent 开始真正跑通
And then when coding agents started to work recently,
我们关停了像 Sora 这样我们同样很兴奋的东西
we shut down things like Sora that we were also really excited about
还有浏览器，就为了全力做这件事，这很难做到
and the browser to really work on this and that is difficult to do.
比如说你往像 Sora 这样的新业务投了 10 亿美元
Um, let's say you invest $1 billion into some new business like Sora,
你怎么判断那项业务会不会成为 OpenAI 的支柱
how do you decide whether or not that business is going to like become a, you know, OpenAI pillar.
不会的，不会，它不会特别成功
Oh, it wouldn't be. No, no, it wouldn't be super successful.
只是把算力投进去更重要
It was just like it was more important to put the compute
把精力投到编程 agent 上，带我进那种会议里看看
and the energy into coding agents take me into one of those meetings.
想象一下你就在那场会议里
Like, imagine you're in that meeting.
我猜也许你就在那场会里
I guess maybe you were in that meeting
你说我们在这件事上花了一年多，投入了巨额资金
where you are saying we've spent a year plus on this thing, huge amounts of money,
大量算力、大量人力和资源，积累了很多势头
huge amounts of compute, lots of people and resources, a lot of momentum into it,
用户在用，也很喜欢
people use it, they love it.
然后你决定叫停，这种决定你怎么做
And then you decide we're gonna pull the plug. Like how do you make that call?
对，这不是一场会就能定的事
Yeah, it's not like a, it's not, it's not a one meeting thing.
我觉得这是一个真正的
It's like a, I think it's a real,
是一种逐渐形成的认识
it's like a somewhat gradual realization
意识到这些算力有更重要的用途
that there is a more important use of this compute.
这些人，这个产品方向
These people, you know, this product direction,
我们要做一个非常痛苦的决定才能走到那一步
and we're gonna make a very painful decision to get there.
一旦你不得不这么做，你怎么重新调动大家
How do you realign people once you do have to, like,
相当于扼杀了他们的心血，再把他们转去做另一个项目
kind of kill their baby to move them to another baby,
大家其实理解使命和其中的利害
people kind of understand the mission and the stakes
也理解需要重新调整方向才能达成，所以即便他们
and the need to reorient to get there. So even if they're like.
当下不开心，有时候他们其实很高兴，有时候会说，对
Unhappy in the moment sometimes they're very happy. Sometimes like, yeah,
这对使命来说是对的事
this is the right thing for the mission.
但即使当下不开心，他们也会说，我明白我们为什么这么做
But even if they're unhappy in the moment, they're like, I get why we're doing this,
而持续把重心转向 super intelligence 是件好事
and the kind of continuing refocus towards super intelligence is like a good thing.
你觉得现在有些项目会被砍掉吗
Do you think that there's gonna be projects currently that are gonna get killed?
我想会的，为了去追求别的，对
I assume so. In order to pursue. Yeah.
John Collison 有一句很棒的话
There's this amazing line from John Collison where he said,
基本上世界上的一切，你环顾四周就会发现
basically everything in the world, if you just look around,
把事情做成实在太难了
it's like so difficult to make things happen.
哪怕只是造一张公园长椅，都难得不可思议
Even like getting so difficult park bench built, it's incredibly difficult.
所以当你环顾四周，你可以把这个世界
And so when you look around, you can kind of think of the world
想象成一个由无数热爱驱动的项目组成的世界
as like a universe of passion projects.
我觉得如果你处在类似 Steve Jobs 那样的位置
And I think that if you are in like Steve Jobs-esque position where you're gonna,
要打造一样十亿人可能每天都会去用的东西
like, create something where a billion people might interact with it every single
而且每天用好几个小时
day for, like, hours.
你就必须深入思考，我要怎么
You have to, like, think deeply about how do I, like,
设计出人们会喜欢、最好也不会让他们不快的东西
design something that people are going to love and ideally not be unhappy about?
你是怎么看待设计的
How do you think about design?
我觉得能和 Jony Ive 一起做设计非常幸运
I feel super lucky to get to work with Johnny Ive on designing.
设计各种东西
Things.
我从他身上学到很多，学到他是怎么真正研究一个问题的
And I have Learned so much from him about how he really studies a problem
在他去找解决方案之前
before trying to get to the solution and not,
他甚至不让自己太早去想解决方案，直到他真正把问题
not even letting him think too much about the solution until he really designs,
真正理解透彻
really understands the problem.
我觉得这是我以前没意识到的关键
And I think this is a key that I didn't appreciate before.
真正好的设计，更多在于理解问题，而不是灵光一闪
Like, really great design is way more about understanding the problem than the flash of insight.
如果你急着扑向答案，或过早把自己锁死在某个方案上
And if you try to rush towards the thing or lock yourself too much into the thing,
你就做不出同样好的成果
um, you will not do as good of a job.
我认为 iPhone 是人类迄今共同造出的最伟大的技术产品
I think the iPhone is the greatest piece of technology humanity has collectively yet made.
它是个了不起的东西
It is incredible thing.
但我已经不再喜欢自己和它的关系了
But I don't like love my relationship with it anymore.
我关掉了通知，所以现在我其实喜欢它多了，对
I turned off my notifications. So I actually like it much better now. Yeah,
我一直开着勿扰模式
I keep myself on do not disturb.
那都还不够，我就
That wasn't even enough. I just like,
我关掉了几乎所有通知，只留极少数几样
I turned off notifications for everything except a very small number of things.
我从来不开通知，因为我，你懂的
And I never have them on because I just, you know,
我想看的时候可以自己去看
I can like look at it if I want to look at it.
连消息应用也是
Even messages apps.
那简直是一次巨大的生活升级
That was like a big life upgrade.
我把 TikTok 删了，因为它实在太强了
And I deleted TikTok because it was just like too powerful.
你之前沉迷 TikTok，我……
Uh, you were addicted to TikTok, you know, I.
我们做 Sora app 的时候发生了件疯狂的事
Uh, so here's a crazy thing that happened when we were building the Sora app.
我逼自己沉迷 TikTok，因为我就想学一学
I made myself get addicted to TikTok because I wanted to just, like learn.
我之前其实从没真正用过它
Like I was like, you know, I, I never really used it before.
顶多是有人发我一个 TikTok 视频之类的
I mean, I had like people would send me a TikTok or whatever,
但我从没被它吸进去
but I never got sucked into it.
我当时想，我真的不想做出那种
And I was like, I really don't want to build something that is gonna have
会吞掉人们时间的东西，可是……
that kind of thing absorb people's time, but not. And.
但我爱上它了，我爱 TikTok，我真觉得它很棒
I loved it. I loved TikTok. I really thought it was great. Um,
然后我以为自己能控制它
and then I thought I could like control it.
我想，哦，这其实还挺好玩的
I was like, oh, you know, it's actually kind of fun,
但我只在睡前放松时用个十分钟
but I only use it for like 10 minutes to wind down before bed
而且我完全能掌控它
and I'm like totally in control of it.
然后有天晚上就变成了一小时
And then it was like an hour one night
再后来某个周六下午，我在沙发上刷了差不多三小时
and then some Saturday afternoon I was on the couch for like three hours
我就想，这真的不是我心中 iPhone 该有的样子
and I was like, this is, like, really not what I thought the iPhone was supposed to be about.
当下我确实很享受，像嗑药一样，但我能看出它对我有害
No, I'm really enjoying in the moment like a drug. But I can tell it's bad for me.
然后我短暂地又把它控制住了，降到大概五分钟
And then I like briefly got it back under control and I was down to, like, 5,
一晚十分钟之类的，就睡前放松一下
10 minutes a night, whatever, you know, like a little wind down before bed.
然后我就想，够了
Then I was just like, enough.
我觉得 iPhone 很了不起，但我觉得自己没有足够的自控力
I think the iPhone is amazing and yet I did not feel like I had enough self control
去留着那个 app，我也不觉得消息应用的通知
to keep that app or I did not feel like the notifications on messaging apps were
对我来说是净收益
like a net good thing for me.
我相信我们会做出一整套了不起的、漂亮的、真正有用的
And I'm sure we will make an incredible, beautiful, like really helpful,
能赋能人的设备
empowering set of devices.
我也确信有人会滥用它们
And I'm also sure that people will misuse them
会以我们想象不到的方式让人们的生活变糟
and it'll make people's lives worse in ways we can't imagine.
我们会适应，但强大的技术就是这样
And we'll adapt. But this is a thing about powerful technology.
你们在发明一种新设备
You're inventing a new device.
如果你是 Johnny，探索这个问题空间的过程是怎样的
What is that process of exploration through the problem space like if you're Johnny?
我不替他回答
I don't answer on his behalf.
不过他之前多少聊过一些，这是他的流程
Um, but okay, he's like talked about this before somewhat, but it's like his process,
比如他在做一辆车时
you know, when he's doing the car,
他会去研究整个赛车运动史
he will like go study all the history of motorsport
然后是各种不同的字体
and then like the different typefaces
人们用在车厢内文字上的字体，还有材料
that people use for the text in the cabin of a car and the materials.
以及原因，还有引擎多年来发出的各种声音
And why and like the diff different sounds that engines have made over time
为什么有些声音更打动人
and why some have appealed.
他真的会把这些探索写成一本本书
I mean, he'll write literal books of all his explorations of all of these like
全是这些细到难以置信的小部件
unbelievably detailed small components.
你们是不是基本上拿了这些书
Did you guys basically take those books and like, try to,
把它们当训练数据，去做一个 Johnny 模型
like use them as training data to make, like, a Johnny model?
没有，不过那倒是很值得一试
Um, no, but that would be a great thing to try there.
是的，他的流程里确实有一部分我搞不懂
Yeah, there is definitely a part of his process that I don't understand.
研究这部分我能理解
Like I understand the studying.
把一个很新的概念打磨成很棒的东西，我也能理解
I understand the refinement of a very new concept into something great.
但中间有一步
But there is like a middle step,
从真正吃透问题到那个极其新颖的想法之间的灵感
the inspiration that comes from understanding the problem really well to the like
在我看来像是一瞬间就冒出来的
very novel idea kind of that seems to me to happen all at once.
我不明白，当你在构思设计一样东西时
And I don't understand that when you're thinking about designing something, how,
你脑子里在想什么
what goes through your mind?
反正我不是设计师
I'm not a designer anyway.
我不会，我不，我，呃
I would, I would not, I, I, uh,
我尽量清楚地认识到自己不擅长什么
I try to be like pretty good about realizing what I'm not good at and I,
这方面我不会有太强的看法
I wouldn't try to have a strong opinion there.
在做公司这一面，你最不擅长什么
What are you the worst at on the business building side?
也许是产品
Maybe product.
真的吗？也许吧
Really? Maybe.
好，如果你不擅长产品，怎么找到优秀的产品人
Okay. How do you find great product people if you're bad at product?
这一点我一直和别人看法不同
This is a thing that I've never quite agreed with people on.
商界有种说法
There's like, there's like a, there's like a business meme
说你只能招你深刻理解的领域里的人
that you can only hire people in things that you deeply understand.
我觉得只要他们够优秀，这显然不成立
I think it, you know, if they're great. I think this is just clearly not true.
我也不懂设计，但我知道 Johnny 设计得很好
I don't understand design either. I know Johnny's great design.
有很多东西我能指出来
Like there's lots of things I can point to.
你跟他聊上 30 分钟
And you talk to him for 30 minutes,
很明显能看出哪些事你要主动去变强
it's very obvious which things do you try to actively get better at and then
哪些事你只需要外包出去，然后接受一点
which things do you just try to outsource and understand
那就是你永远成不了顶尖
that you're just never gonna be one of the best.
我坚信你该在自己的强项上继续变强
I am a big believer in you should try to get better at your strengths and the whole,
而那种执念，非要去补
like, obsession with I'm gonna get better at the things
那些你根本不擅长、也永远不会擅长的东西
that I'm just not good at all and never gonna be good at.
那是巨大的陷阱，把强项做到极致就好
Huge trap, super good at your strengths. Okay,
如果非要排个序，你最大的强项是什么
what are your biggest strengths if you had to like force rank?
我讨厌这个问题，不是出于假谦虚
I hate this question. Um, I don't hate this from a false modesty perspective.
而是要对自己的强项说出点洞见，真的很难
I think it's, like, very hard to say anything insightful about your own strengths.
你显然很擅长把人凝聚到某个目标上
You're clearly good at really rallying people around some objective.
是的
Sure.
但我不觉得我能教会一个不擅长这个的人
Uh, but I don't like, I don't think I could teach someone who isn't good at
怎么把这件事做好
that how to be good at that.
那些对某人来说天生就会的事，很难
I think the things that come supernaturally to someone are very hard to,
我说不好，至少就我自己而言
I don't know, or at least in my own case,
我并不真正理解自己为什么擅长这个，也不知道该拿它怎么办
I don't like deeply understand why I'm good at that or what to do about it.
不过我们前面聊过这一类东西
Although I think we talked about earlier like this category of things
你能学会，但没法被教会
that you can learn but you can't teach.
我觉得理解这点很重要
I think this is quite important to understand and like
如果你想在这类事上变强，让别人给你讲解
if you want to get good at something like that, asking someone to explain it to you,
依我的经验，从来没用
in my experience, never works.
真正去研究他们，跟他们一起开会
Really studying them and like sitting with them in meetings
然后自己去观察、去学
and just trying to observe it and learn it yourself.
这才管用
That does work.
每当有件事我确实想变强
Um, but, and like when there has been something that I do want to get better at,
我都会去靠近那个做得很好的人，深入研究他
I have tried to just be around someone who's great at it and really deeply study it.
但我不觉得他们能把这事讲清楚给我听
But I don't think they would have been able to explain it to me.
我不觉得靠跟我聊他们就能教会我
I don't think they could have like taught it to me by talking to me about it.
我觉得完全对
I think that's totally right.
你看世界顶尖玩家怎么学游戏
If you look at like the way that the best people in the world learn video games,
比如你玩 CS:GO，你先自己打几局
if you're playing, like, CS go, you, like, play some CS go.
掌握基本的游戏机制，然后去看职业选手
So you have like the basic game dynamics and then you just go watch a pro
看他们在地图上怎么走位
and like see how they interact on the map.
在不同阶段百分之百地去研究
hundred % at different points in the game and stuff.
说到组织、节奏，还有野心
When you think about like organization, pace, you know, there's like ambition,
这些东西，你理想中希望你的组织随时间推进
all these other things, but like you ideally over time want your organization.
你当然不希望它变慢，最好还能越跑越快
You obviously don't want it to slow down, but ideally it even moves faster.
这怎么做到？我觉得九成取决于你放在领导岗上的人
How do you like bake that in? I think it's like 90% the people you put in leadership roles.
好，还有些别的办法
Okay, there's like other things you can do.
大家有各种不同的运作节奏
People have all these different sort of operating rhythms
各种经营公司的方式、各种管理技巧
and how they try to run the company and this management technique and that one.
但我觉得，最终主要还是取决于人
And I think it's, I think mostly just comes down to the people.
对每个坐在那种位置上的人，我一定会想的一点是
Definitely something I think about with everybody in a role like that is like,
他们是行动快的人，还是慢的人
are they a fast mover or a slow mover?
如果没跟他们共事过，你怎么判断这点
How do you measure that without actually having worked with them in the past?
理想情况是你以前跟他们共事过，多数时候是这样
Well, ideally, you have worked them in the past. I think most of the time.
公司的高管应该内部提拔，而不是外部招聘
Executives at a company should be promoted internally, not hired externally. Okay.
但当你确实需要从外部招人时
Um, but when you do need to hire someone externally,
你会花很多时间跟他们聊，花很多时间做背景调查
you spend a lot of time talking to them, spend a lot of time reference checking.
你会试着以某种轻松的方式先一起合作
You try to like work together in some kind of casual way.
换个话题，过去 12 个月里
Slightly different note, what was the most painful thing
最痛苦的事是什么
that happened in the last 12 months?
老实说，一边养孩子一边拼命工作太折磨人了
Honestly, having kids and working really hard at the same time is brutal.
真的极其痛苦
It's just extremely painful.
相对来说，我觉得我算是个陪伴很多的爸爸
Like you know your kids, and I think I'm like a very present dad relative.
现在我基本上除了工作就是陪家人，别的都不做
Like I don't do anything but work and hang out with my family really at this point.
但我还是觉得错过了太多，这可是一生只有一次的事
But I still feel like I'm missing so much of this like one time thing.
举个例子，想到像 Masa 这样的人时会很有感触
It's very painful when you think of someone like Masa, for example.
他的脑子和看待世界的方式太不一样了
What about like his brain and the way that he sees the world is so different.
我觉得他最终会成为这个十年里最疯狂的成功者之一
I think he will end up being like one of the wild successes of this decade.
对，了不起的人，是我很珍视的朋友，了不起的人
Yeah, incredible person. Yeah. Dear friend. Incredible person.
极强的信念，对大数字和大规模一点都不怕
Massive conviction and belief and not afraid at all of big numbers and scale.
这非常棒
And it's great.
世界上像 Masa 这样的人不多
Uh, there are not many Masa like people in the world
我们应该非常感激有他们
and we should be very grateful for them.
是什么让他成了这样，我不知道你有没有跟他聊过
What made him like, what, I don't know if you've like talked with him,
但就我看来，他一直都是这个样子
but, uh, I mean, as far as I can tell, he was like always like this.
你是不是也有那种完全没有上限的概念
Do you also have the same sort of just like no concept,
对规模没有天花板的概念
like no ceiling concept of scale?
我没有，我觉得 Masa 是独一类的人
Not I. I think Masa is like a n of 1 character.
你会不会把 OpenAI 看成有点像那只会下金蛋的鹅
Do you kind of view OpenAI as a little bit like the golden goose?
怎么说
In what way?
随着时间不断孵化出一堆非常有价值的东西
Um, spawning a bunch of very valuable things over time
并打造出一种核心能力，让世界上的智能不断提升
and just building like a core competency of increasing intelligence in the world.
我不太是这么想的，但我懂你的意思
Not really how I think of it. I get what you're saying.
但感觉我们不只是在不停下金蛋
But it doesn't feel like we're just like spitting out golden eggs.
感觉我们是在建一种会复利增长的东西
It feels like we're building this kind of compounding thing.
我从你这儿学到的最喜欢的思维模型之一
I think one of my favorite mental models
就是真实趋势与虚假趋势这个概念
that I've taken from you is this idea of real trends versus fake trends.
对，这确实很重要
And oh yeah, this is an important thing.
每当有人谈泡沫或别的什么
Like whenever people talked about bubbles or anything else,
我总是有点困惑
I was always kind of confused.
我研究过很多 Warren Buffett 和 Charlie Munger
Like I studied Warren Buffett and Charlie Munger a bunch,
他们特别爱谈泡沫和被高估的东西
and so they love to talk about bubbles and things being overvalued.
我一直想搞明白，你怎么判断一样东西是真实的
I was trying to like decipher how do you figure out whether or not something is real
还是虚假的，它会不会持续下去，还是只会
or fake and whether or not it's going to persist and continue or it's just going to, you know.
回归均值，以及你是怎么想通的
Revert to the mean and what you figure out.
我觉得你的思维模型基本上是
Well, it was, I think your mental model of basically
关于什么是真实趋势、什么是虚假趋势
if there's a small group of people, like what is a real trend versus a fake trend.
虚假趋势就像 VR 那样，炒作很多
A fake trend is, you know, the VR situation where someone, there's a lot of hype,
但有人买了之后，并不是真的喜欢
but then someone buys the thing, they don't really love it.
他们不会真的开始
They don't really start to, like,
围绕使用体验重新安排生活，然后它就被搁在一边了
design their life around the experience of using it and then it sits on the shelf.
而对我来说 ChatGPT 就不一样
Whereas like for me with ChatGPT,
我几乎每天都用，有时候需要大量工作
it's pretty much every day and maybe for like sometimes I need to work a lot,
就用上三个小时，有些天几乎不用
so I spend like three hours or some days it's like almost nothing
但它一直存在于我的生活里，你是怎么判断的
but it's like there persistent in my life. How do you kind of like figure out.
现在在公司内部怎么判断某样东西是真实趋势还是虚假趋势
Now whether or not something is a real trend or a fake trend inside of the company
大体上是同一个原则，看它是否真的有深层、持久的
and just generally same principle like is there real deep, enduring,
你是怎么形成这套理念或思维框架的
how did you come to that philosophy or mental framework?
我看过大量创业公司
Well, I like kind of watched a lot of startups.
在 YC 工作有很多很棒的地方
Uh, the there are many amazing things about working at YC,
尤其是你能拿到的数据量
but just the amount of data you get.
只要你愿意花时间去分析它
And as long as you're willing to like spend the time trying to analyze it
把它理清楚，你真的能搞明白很多事
and make sense of it, you can really figure out a lot of things.
有没有哪些你以前有的大思维框架
Are there any big mental frameworks that you used to have
你现在觉得在当下环境里是错的，而且还会继续
that you think are wrong in today's environment and will be continue,
随着智能爆炸，它们会越来越站不住脚
continue to get more wrong over time as intelligence explodes.
我觉得其中很大一部分都是这样
I mean, I kind of think a huge amount of them.
它们在当时不一定是错的
Are they weren't necessarily wrong at the time,
当然我也肯定有一堆地方是错的
although I'm sure I was wrong about a bunch of things too.
但现在它们中很大一部分都错了
But a huge amount of them are wrong now.
我觉得今天的创业公司大体上还是像十年前的创业公司
I think a startup of today still looks mostly like a startup of 10 years ago
因为主流经验就是这么教你的
because that's what the received wisdom says you're supposed to do.
当然，在某些方面确实不一样
And sure, it's different in some ways.
大家会说，我要少招点人
People are like, well, I'm going to hire less people
把更多钱花在 Codex 的 token 之类的东西上
and spend more money on tokens for Codex or whatever,
但它本该看起来非常不同才对
but it should probably look very different.
我确实见过一些人在用完全不同的方式创业
And I have met a few people who are trying to do a startup in a completely different
但大多数人只是多用一点 Codex
way, but most people just use means like use more Codex and
这看起来还远远不够
that doesn't seem like enough.